<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Linux Foundation | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/linux-foundation/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/linux-foundation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Linux Foundation</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Linux Foundation</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/linux-foundation/</link></image><item><title>Pathways to Cybersecurity: Best Practices in Open Source</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/pathways-to-cybersecurity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/pathways-to-cybersecurity/</guid><description>&lt;p>The European Union’s Cyber Resilience Act (CRA) presents a
watershed moment for the open source ecosystem, imposing
rigorous cybersecurity requirements on products with digital
elements (PDEs) commercialized in the EU. While the regulation
will not fully apply until December 2027, with certain provisions
taking effect earlier, the stakes are enormous—penalties
reaching €15 million or 2.5% of global annual turnover for non-compliance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The regulation’s impact extends beyond documentation and
vulnerability reporting. It fundamentally alters the relationship
between upstream open source projects and downstream commercial
adopters, demanding greater collaboration for sustainable
security maintenance. Neither manufacturers nor stewards
can meet CRA requirements in isolation—manufacturers must
conduct due diligence when integrating open source components,
while stewards must implement and document cybersecurity
policies that facilitate secure development.
The Linux Foundation’s analysis of three flagship projects—Civil
Infrastructure Platform (CIP), Yocto Project, and Zephyr Project—reveals
both the readiness and challenges facing open
source software stewards under the new regulatory framework.
The CRA introduces a novel distinction between commercial
manufacturers who bear primary responsibility for product
compliance, and open source software stewards who develop
and maintain open source software without monetization. This
acknowledges the reality that open source components often
constitute up to 96% of modern software while respecting the
fundamental openness of the development model.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>World of Open Source: Open Source Maturity in Europe</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/oss-europe-2024/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/oss-europe-2024/</guid><description>&lt;p>For the past three years, LF Research has conducted a study on the
adoption, opportunities, and perceptions of open source across
Europe. The trend is clear in 2024: the perceived value of open source
continues to increase in the region, and stakeholders across sectors
and industries can see the importance of investing in it. This year&amp;rsquo;s
report identifies key sectors to channel this investment, the
opportunity for the public sector to embrace open source for digital
public goods, and how regulations are interacting with and responding
to more widespread open source adoption and knowledge. With insights
taken from the 2024 World of Open Source survey and augmented by
interviews with over a dozen experts working in open source, this
report unpacks the current state of open source in Europe and
highlights next steps to improve adoption, understanding, and
regulation for open source as this technological space continues to
mature. Read the report for the full investigation into why open
source has hit a watershed moment in Europe.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>