<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>remote | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/remote/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/remote/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>remote</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 11:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>remote</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/remote/</link></image><item><title>Video conferencing at scale - A practical guide</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2020-03-15-how-to-video-conference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2020-03-15-how-to-video-conference/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are video conferencing day-in day-out now. Small conversations via
video call are a regular part of remote work. In times of restricted
travel and polluted air, this is excellent. It also works pretty well
for two or three people. With 6, it gets difficult to manage who
speaks. Above ten, things get tricky both from a technical as well as
a social perspective.
We have all been in this call
where there was an echo that blew everybody&amp;rsquo;s ears off, except for
that one person that did not hear it (it was them). I have collected a
few technical tips and practises over time that may help make video
conferences easier and more enjoyable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In situations with a small number of participants, there will be few
technical issues. The technology for video conferencing handles such
setups quite well. Group size is also a social matter &amp;ndash; it is easy to
ask your buddy in the one-to-one to hang on a second while you silence
the phone. In a call with 20 people, it is rude to have the phone ring
in the first place. So let&amp;rsquo;s be spoiled brats here and look at the
finer things in demanding situations:&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="basics">Basics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are two main contributors to enjoyable video conferencing,
network and media, as in audio and video. Both start to act up with
more participants because network use increases with the number of
participants and audio adds up as well from multiple sources. Let&amp;rsquo;s
break it down.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="A video-conferencing headset." srcset="
/media/img/post/2020-video-conferencing-setup_hu885464ce4460ce61367e8b827b9c29fb_809661_9b4edc9ac0c7c9b51dfdf04f94c24db5.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2020-video-conferencing-setup_hu885464ce4460ce61367e8b827b9c29fb_809661_543b5bc4997a92f98a74f0b9411f5d60.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2020-video-conferencing-setup_hu885464ce4460ce61367e8b827b9c29fb_809661_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2020-video-conferencing-setup_hu885464ce4460ce61367e8b827b9c29fb_809661_9b4edc9ac0c7c9b51dfdf04f94c24db5.webp"
width="80%"
height="560"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="networking">Networking&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Choppy audio or hanging video often indicate issues with networking
(or too much load on the computer, but that is less common
today). Network issues can be related to bandwidth, latency and
stability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regarding &lt;em>bandwidth&lt;/em>, a good audio stream requires a couple of KB per
second, while a good video stream requires 100s of KB to tens of MBs
per second. For video connections, the requirements add up with the
number of participants and quickly reach the limits of slower internet
connections. If the choppiness reduces when video is turned off, it
indicates an issue with network bandwith. Bandwidth has a weakest link
problem, it is limited by the slowest element in the connection between
the participants. For example, if a computer is tethered to the
internet connection of a mobile phone, the wifi connection between the
computer and the phone may look faster than the internet connection
speed of the phone which then becomes the bottleneck.
Most commonly, bandwidth at the internet provider
is quite reliable and fast, so that the limits should be located
between the internet access point and the computer.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>For wifi connections, make sure there is plenty of reserve bandwidth
above that constantly needed for conferencing. Other applications
also use bandwidth. Loading a larger web page can be demonstrated to
temporarily cause choppy video in a conference. As a rule of thumb,
wifi should be at least at 100MB per second, ideally way
higher. Keep in mind that wifi speed drops as the distance to the
access point increases. Moving around the house or cafe may affect
the available bandwidth.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Phone internet connections are suitable for one-to-ones. For more
participants, they can quickly exhaust network bandwidth and may
rack up volume-based data fees. They also make everybody else&amp;rsquo;s
experience miserable because the camera usually zooms in on your
nose hair.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wired network connections are great because they do not degrade with
distance and provide fast, consistent speed. One check for
potential wifi issues is to temporarily connect the computer to the
internet access point using a network cable and see if the
conference quality improves.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Latency&lt;/em>, or network delay, is also a potential problem. It is
usually low enough for wifi and wired internet connections and can be
low to horrendous on mobile. There is not much that can be done about
it from the users side.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Network &lt;em>stability&lt;/em> (basically all aspects in how your network
connection quality may change while the conference is in progress) can
become a real nuisance. Especially for longer video conferences
like the 8-hour one I just attended a lot of disturbances can
happen. For example, a badly shielded vacuum cleaner may interfere
with wireless network. Murphy&amp;rsquo;s law has it that your neighbour will
always start vacuuming 10 minutes into the call. Another interference
may be network traffic by other users. Wifi bandwidth is shared and
can be eaten up if family members create a lot of other
traffic. Reducing the Netflix subscription to only one stream may help
here :-) In general, relying on bandwidth to be constantly available
is a bit risky. Also here, using a wired connection circumvents some
of the problems, since it (usually) does not share bandwidth with
other computers on the local network.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a good rule of thumb, more bandwidth (a faster internet connection)
is always better, and wired network beats everything in terms of
consistent quality and stability. Go wired or sit close to the wifi
access point.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="video">Video&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Video depends mostly on hardware and system load, provided the
computer can handle processing the video data. In most
cases, if video quality degrades, it is not because of hardware
issues, but because the software decides the computer or the network
cannot handle a higher resolution and switches to a lower
one. Consider shutting down unnecessary programs, especially if you
are low on memory. The task manager or activity monitor display memory
and processor usage and indicate if the computer is
overloaded. High-quality video uses exponentially more computing power
and bandwidth depending on the resolution, so reducing video quality
along the usual steps (ultra-&amp;gt;HD-&amp;gt;SD-&amp;gt;whateveritiscalled) will result
in much lower requirements.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="audio">Audio&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Audio is often the most difficult issue because it usually works just fine
in test situations and then causes problems during the
conference. Key issues are feedback, background noise and foreground
noise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Audio feedback loops&lt;/em> are the worst. They range from a simple
annoying echo to techno-music-like loops that get increasingly
louder. This is caused by the microphone picking up the output of the
speakers, retransmitting it to the audience so that it is played by
the speakers again with a delay and this way
causing a never-ending loop. It gets louder if the volume of the next
round is higher than before and softer if it is lower. It can be
anything from a decreasing echo to a cacophony.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This also indicates the remedy to feedback: In a conference settings
where the participants all attend remotely, the audio of the
conference should &lt;em>never&lt;/em> come from speakers so that the microphone
can pick it up. Use a headset instead. Always. If you take one thing
away from this guide, it should be to always use a headset for video
conferencing with groups. Use in-ears if you don&amp;rsquo;t like headphone
hair.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Conferencing software has audio echo cancellation (feedback
suppression) built in. It works ok, but not in all
situations. Sometimes it slips in the middle of a call just for a
second, but long enough for you to hear yourself speak with some delay
or to deafen the whole audience. Better not to rely on it - keep it
simple and use a headset.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Foreground noise&lt;/em> is one thing that throws off software echo
cancellation at times. Foreground noise is ambient sound that
originates from close to or the casing of the microphone. Ideally the
only foreground noise should be what you say. However, the built-in
microphones is located within to the computer and picks up typing on
the keyboard or anything else your hands do very loudly. Such noises
appear a lot louder to the audience than to you because they are
partially filtered by our hearing. Another problem with the built-in
microphone being integrated in the computer case is that it picks up
typing, rattling and anything physical going on on the desk the
computer sits on. The remedy to this is the same as to echo &amp;ndash; use a
headset that also has a built-in microphone. This separates the
microphone from the computer casing and locates it much closer to your
mouth and further away from the keyboard. So again &amp;ndash; use a headset,
now with a microphone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Background noise&lt;/em> is caused by whatever happens in your environment
during the call. Your phone notifications, people walking by or
talking to each other, clocks ticking, all of this will be picked up and
transmitted to the audience. And it adds up if their are many. It is a
matter of courtesie as well to avoid that as much as possible. There
are three remedies: Mute yourself when you are not talking. Reduce
background noise by picking a quiet room or moving further away from
the sources. Keep your microphone close to your mouth (headset&amp;hellip;) so
that the microphone volume can be lowered as much as possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="setup">Setup&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If the calls are important, consider doing a trial run where you
participate on the other end. Try out typing, talking to other people
in the room, shuffling things on the desk and all the other things
that could go wrong. Especially if the setup is going to be used
often, it is worth spending time to make sure it works really well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Keep in mind that it may appear on &lt;em>your end&lt;/em> that the built-in
speakers and microphone work just fine but it may make the experience
for everybody else on the call miserable with your voice being choppy
and overlaid by typing noises.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For indoor use, gamer headsets offer a great combination of
comfortable, high-quality headphones with good microphones that can be
worn for a few hours without becoming annoying.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Interestingly, the choice of specific video conferencing tool does not
matter that much. Modern web or app based systems work pretty much the
same, as long as the discussed technical aspects are taken care
of.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="summary">Summary&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To sum up, there are four key steps towards better video
conferencing with larger groups:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Use a headset with a microphone close, but not too close to your
mouth. Avoid using the built-in speakers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Use a wired network connection or ensure a very good connection to
the wifi network. Avoid mobile networks for this use case.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Use a headset (or stand-alone) microphone and avoid the built-in
microphone of the computer to reduce foreground noise.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ensure a quiet environment and mute yourself when not speaking.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Finally, it will be helpful to consider online meeting etiquette. If
you participate in a call, make time for it. Put your phone on
do-not-disturb during the call and focus your attention on what is
being discussed. Combined with a solid technical setup, this should
make video conferences a lot more enjoyable.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>