<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>SEP | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/sep/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/sep/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>SEP</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>SEP</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/sep/</link></image><item><title>FOSS, standard essential patents and FRAND in the European Union</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2018-jrc-workshop/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2018-jrc-workshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of the research project
on
&lt;a href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/">&amp;ldquo;The Interaction between Open Source Software and FRAND licensing in Standardisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>,
a workshop was organised by the European Commission, Joint Research
Centre (JRC) in collaboration with Directorate General Communications
Networks, Content and Technology (CONNECT) to present and discuss the
intermediate results to date. The workshop took place in Brussels on
September 18, 2018. I presented a set of observations from the research on
the case studies performed as part of the project that are outlined
below. Other speakers
where
&lt;a href="https://www.the-klu.org/faculty-research/resident-faculty/catharina-maracke/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Catharina Maracke&lt;/a> on
the issue of legal compliance between Open Source and FRAND
licenses, &lt;a href="https://perens.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bruce Perens&lt;/a> on &amp;ldquo;Community Dynamics
in Open Source&amp;rdquo;,
and &lt;a href="https://www.gesmer.com/team/andrew-s-updegrove" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Andy Updegrove&lt;/a>
on &amp;ldquo;Dynamics in Standardisation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You may ask what the relevance of this debate is for the wider Free
and Open Source Software community. The obvious answer is that to
distribute
software
&lt;a href="https://opensource.com/article/18/3/patent-grant-mit-license" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;without restriction&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>,
the user needs all the usage rights associated with the program. While
most FOSS contributors assume that this is naturally the central
motivation for anybody to contribute in the first place, there is a
long history of attempts to maintain some sort of exclusive control
over a piece of FOSS code, possibly using other rights than copyright.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Contributor license agreements (CLA) are a well known instrument for
that. The original author agrees to an exclusive or non-exclusive
license to a central entity (usually a community organisation or a
dominating company) to use their work. This may just give a community
organisation a right to adopt newer licenses. Or it may give
a
&lt;a href="https://dirkriehle.com/publications/2009-selected/the-commercial-open-source-business-model/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">single Open Source vendor&lt;/a> the
right to use other contributor&amp;rsquo;s work commercially. Whether CLA embody
FOSS culture or violate them by creating an asymmetric distribution of
benefits between contributors and a company therefore depends on the
specific terms of the
CLA. The
&lt;a href="http://contributoragreements.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">contributor agreements configurator&lt;/a> helps
projects to set up a CLA and understand what the motivation behind the
terms are (&lt;a href="https://endocode.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Endocode&lt;/a> contributed the
implementation). CLA are controversial, especially if they
include
&lt;a href="https://help.nextcloud.com/t/cla-caa-ca-etc-etc-let-s-get-it-right/588" target="_blank" rel="noopener">copyright assignments to a single company&lt;/a>. Projects
and contributors are well-advised to make sure to fully understand
what they are agreeing to. The main take-away for the argument here is
that the norm in FOSS communities is a &lt;em>symmetric&lt;/em> distribution of
rights between all contributors, and CLA are one instrument to modify
this to the benefit of a single entity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But that is not all. It just helps to explain how such asymmetric
rights can be used to give a single entity more power in a community
of contributors. There is a long history of such attempts, and they
usually involve some other legal rights beyond the terms of the FOSS
license applied. There is a good reason for that: FOSS licenses give
contributors and users a time-tested and well-balanced framework for
collaboration. &lt;a href="https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/basics/4freedoms.en.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;Use, study, modify, redistribute&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> is
a simple, easy to understand mantra that every FOSS contributor knows
and understands. CLA augment the FOSS license terms with an additional
contractual agreement, but for the most part stay in the realm of
copyright just like FOSS licenses. Other instruments not so much:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Trademarks are used to enforce a vendor&amp;rsquo;s expectations when others
adopt and ship their software. This is used by communities to
protect their names, like in
the
&lt;a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/foundation/trademarks/policy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mozilla Trademark Policy&lt;/a>,
or to make sure specific services are included in devices, like in
the
&lt;a href="https://source.android.com/compatibility/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Android Compatibility Program&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Trade secrets like delayed code releases under FOSS licenses or
proprietary &amp;ldquo;extensions&amp;rdquo; that
are
&lt;a href="https://about.mattermost.com/features/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">effectively required for the software to be useful&lt;/a> are
used to maintain an edge of an &amp;ldquo;enterprise&amp;rdquo; version over the FOSS
release.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The
&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/software-patents.en.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">software patents debate&lt;/a> may
have slowed down, but is still relevant. Patents exist, and
applications for patents that include claims that are implemented in
existing FOSS solutions never stopped. It has become harder to be
granted a patent for a software-only solution. Institutions like
the &lt;a href="https://www.openinventionnetwork.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Invention Network&lt;/a>
create a safe space where FOSS innovators cross-license freely and
avoid litigation. However vendors shipping FOSS in products still
need to clear potential patent claims implemented in
those. Conformance with patents does not usually follow from FOSS
licenses.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Which leads to round five of the match with software freedom in one
corner and exclusivity in the other &amp;ndash; standard-essential patents
(SEP). Everybody loves standards, and FOSS especially: We use
standardised programming languages, unicode tables and system call
interfaces. Standards are the foundation for interoperability, and
some standards like
the &lt;a href="http://opendocumentformat.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Document Format&lt;/a> are the
result of a long struggle to establish formats that re-open markets
for competition. All of these standards
are
&lt;a href="https://opensource.com/resources/what-are-open-standards" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Standards&lt;/a> that
can be implemented in FOSS without restrictions. But what if
implementing a standard would be required to interoperate with others,
or even mandatory under existing regulations, and this standard would
include functionality that is covered by patent claims, possibly with
royalty-bearing patent licenses? That is the definition of SEP, which
are commonly required to be licensed either royalty-free or under
&amp;ldquo;fair, reasonable and non-discriminatory&amp;rdquo; (FRAND) licenses. It is also
a relevant and current concern because
the
&lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/docsroom/documents/26583" target="_blank" rel="noopener">European Commission considers SEP under FRAND licenses a useful instrument&lt;/a> for
industrial policy in the European Union. Until now, the wider FOSS
community has contributed some positions to this debate that is for
the most part dominated by incumbent industries, recognized
standards-development organisations (SDO) and policy makers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The study currently conducted under the supervision by
the
&lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/departments/joint-research-centre_en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">European Commission Joint Research Centre (EC-JRC)&lt;/a> on
&lt;a href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/">&amp;ldquo;The Interaction between Open Source Software and FRAND licensing in Standardisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> aims
at providing a better understanding of the interplay between FOSS
licenses, governance and the IPR policies of SDO. At the workshop that
was just held in Brussels as part of this study where an initial set
of case studies on the subject have been presented. Theses case
studies (that I am the author of) will become part of the overall
study report prepared
by
&lt;a href="https://www.inno.tu-berlin.de/menue/about_us/team/prof_dr_rer_pol/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Knut Blind&lt;/a> and
me. As the study progresses, a number of early observations from these
cases will be shared in this blog and other channels. It is important
that the wider FOSS community recognizes the relevance and importance
of this subject and actively makes itself heard. CERN, the ECMAscript
community, the Eclipse Foundation, the Linux Foundation and others
have already contributed insights to the field work for the
project. Others, especially FSFE, have been notably absent from the
debate. The &lt;a href="https://opensource.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Source Initiative&lt;/a> is
represented on the project&amp;rsquo;s steering committee.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The standards that
will be shaped by this debate, like 5G mobile communication or IoT
protocols, will affect us all, as will welfare gains or losses from
policies that influence the innovativeness of FOSS. There are
opportunities to contribute: communities can communicate what their
needs are with regards to standards and FOSS. Contributors can
provide input to the case studies or the stakeholder survey that will
be performed in the next phase of the study. Feel free to reach out if
you would like to participate.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Relationship Between Open Source Software and Standard Setting</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/</guid><description>&lt;p>The objective of the study is to identify possible commonalities and
barriers for interaction between standardisation and open source
processes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The study should clarify the role of open source in the context of
standard setting, in particular its interplay with the licensing of
standards-essential patents under &amp;ldquo;fair, reasonable and
non-discriminatory&amp;rdquo; (FRAND) terms and provide an overview of free and
open source software (FOSS) and FRAND features in standardisation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The study on the interaction between open source software and FRAND
licensing in standardisation is carried out on behalf of the &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/departments/joint-research-centre_en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">European
Commission&amp;rsquo;s Joint Research
Centre&lt;/a>
by &lt;a href="https://www.fokus.fraunhofer.de/en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fraunhofer Institute of Open Communication System
FOKUS&lt;/a> and Mirko Böhm representing
the &lt;a href="https://www.openinventionnetwork.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Invention Network&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Communication about the study:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>European Commission: &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/news/study-role-open-source-standard-setting" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Study on the role of open source in standard setting&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>EU Science Hub: &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/jrc/en/science-update/jrc-study-interaction-between-open-source-software-and-frand-licensing-standardisation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">JRC Study on the Interaction between Open Source Software and FRAND licensing in Standardisation&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Publication of the final report: &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/jrc/en/publication/eur-scientific-and-technical-research-reports/relationship-between-open-source-software-and-standard-setting" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Relationship Between Open Source Software and Standard Setting&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The project was originally named &amp;ldquo;The Interaction between Open Source
Software and FRAND licensing in Standardisation&amp;rdquo;. The title was later
simplified to &amp;ldquo;The Relationship Between Open Source Software and
Standard Setting&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>