<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Europe | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/europe/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/europe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Europe</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Europe</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/europe/</link></image><item><title>Open Source Congress 2025</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2025-09-16-open-source-congress/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2025-09-16-open-source-congress/</guid><description>&lt;p>The third &lt;a href="https://www.opensourcecongress.org/event/2025/open-source-congress-2025" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Source
Congress&lt;/a>
took place in Brussels on 16 September 2025. This annual gathering
brings together code-hosting open source foundations and partners to
align on critical issues facing the ecosystem. After the Linux
Foundation created Open Source Congress in 2023, each year a different
organization has signed up as the host. I would like to thank the
Eclipse Foundation for agreeing to be the host this year. The event
focused on four key topics: open source in a multi-polar world,
cybersecurity, sustainability, and regulation and public policy. The
primary value of such gatherings lies in alignment and exchange rather
than concrete actions. Since Open Source Congress operates under
Chatham House rules and is less accessible than typical open source
events, sharing insights from the discussions serves the wider
community. Below are personal observations from the four panels.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="panel-1---open-source-in-a-multi-polar-world">Panel 1 - Open Source in a Multi-Polar World&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The open source ecosystem was multi-polar from its inception. Key open
source innovations originate from various regions: Ruby from
Japan, Linux and Python from Europe, the GNU Project from the US. The
US tech industry was quicker to realize open source technologies as
a growth driver, allowing US business interests to overlay this
narrative today. However, nothing is inherently polarizing in how the
open source ecosystem works. It serves as both
creative destruction and resilience mechanism, undermining
traditional control structures while remaining largely
unregulable. Cultural and language barriers continue to shape
how and where contributors collaborate, making truly global
collaboration a key challenge. There is optimism
that AI will provide instant translation mechanisms to bridge
such divides. Maintaining arms-length distance from policy making
remains essential to preserve open source&amp;rsquo;s organic governance. At the same
time, regulation will inevitably affect the
ecosystem&amp;rsquo;s global dynamics. The EU Cyber Resilience Act is
the first law explicitly shaping stakeholder roles.
While progress has been made in building capacity and
expertise for open source foundations to engage in policy debates
when necessary, much work remains.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="panel-2---cybersecurity-influencing-best-practices-and-standards">Panel 2 - Cybersecurity: Influencing Best Practices and Standards&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A global race to define cybersecurity standards creates a
maze of regulation across international markets. While this
challenges global manufacturers, open source communities face few
concrete regulatory obligations. However, to enable global adoption of their
releases, they are strongly incentivized to support
downstream users with documentation and sound cybersecurity
practices. Creating an environment conducive to smooth
upstream-downstream collaboration requires open source foundations to
engage in relevant standards development processes that define
implementation details of cybersecurity regulation. This
remains difficult, as most stewards lack both funding and
subject matter expertise for standards development.
The panel revealed tensions between traditional open source
collaboration and emerging bureaucratic frameworks at organizations
like the
&lt;a href="https://unite.un.org/en/news/sixteen-organizations-endorse-un-open-source-principles" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UN&lt;/a>
and &lt;a href="https://www.digitalpublicgoods.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DPGA&lt;/a>, warning that OSS
risks losing its core strengths when bent to external rules. The
discussion emphasized that effective policy engagement should
facilitate organic collaboration and create market-driven incentives
rather than impose rigid bureaucratic structures. Initiatives like
the Linux Foundation&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://alpha-omega.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alpha-Omega&lt;/a> serve as
effective funding instruments that align with open source
principles. In recent years, public initiatives like the German
&lt;a href="https://www.sovereign.tech/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sovereign Tech Agency&lt;/a> increasingly
support under-maintained projects. Under guidance from &lt;a href="https://openforumeurope.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Forum
Europe&lt;/a>, a &lt;a href="https://eu-stf.openforumeurope.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">feasibility
study&lt;/a> has been submitted to the
EU to elevate such activities to the European level with a larger
budget.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="panel-3---sustainability-and-the-open-ecosystem">Panel 3 - Sustainability and the Open Ecosystem&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The sustainability of the open source development model is hotly
debated. The underlying issue appears to be a mix of insufficient funding and a
fundamental &amp;ldquo;matchmaking problem&amp;rdquo; of allocating available funds to
specific projects and contributors efficiently. While
the myth that open source is the unpaid labor of love of hobbyist
maintainers still percolates, the 2024 &lt;a href="https://opensourcefundingsurvey2024.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Source Software Funding
Survey&lt;/a> shows that 86% of
contribution value comes from employee labor. This study raises challenging
questions. On one hand, what will be the effect of 50m€ public funding
initiatives if $7.7B is invested by private industry
annually? On the other hand, if more funding becomes available, how
will it be distributed? Grant making will profoundly impact
the viability of individual projects, raising concerns about
public sector actors&amp;rsquo; ability to effectively disperse
sovereign-tech-fund-like funds where they are needed most, rather
than to favored champions or consultancies specializing in grant
acquisition. However, such initiatives will likely support
ecosystem diversity and grassroots initiatives, which may
be a benefit worth the cost.
Some funding programs focus on maintenance or security, creating
a risk of fragmenting development work by separating improvement,
maintenance, and security responsibilities. Since implementing new
features is always most fascinating, the impression that maintenance
and cybersecurity are somebody else&amp;rsquo;s problem must be avoided.
Emerging models favor market-driven approaches like
the EU CRA, which creates business incentives for maintenance work and
eliminates freeloading, potentially contributing more to
open source sustainability than public spending programs that struggle
with coordination and measurement challenges.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="panel-4---regulation-and-public-policy">Panel 4 - Regulation and Public Policy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The final session was essentially a moderated Q&amp;amp;A round. A cluster of
questions evolved around how external forces now influencing the open
source world will reshape open collaboration dynamics. The
release-early-release-often, show-me-the-code mentality drives
experimentation and a somewhat Darwinian trial-and-error approach to
identifying promising projects. Voluntary participation ensures that
projects receive attention according to their value to the
community. Interestingly, funding programs based on selective awards
are expected to bias these mechanisms more than market access
regulation. Future research is needed to verify this expectation.
However, regulatory approaches will fundamentally reshape the
ecosystem by influencing adoption criteria for components, driving
consolidation of fragmented libraries into fewer, more maintainable
packages and addressing collective action problems around
responsibility and decision-making in policy advocacy. This will
affect different communities differently, depending on factors like the
granularity and maintainer base of package repositories. However, there
is a prevailing assumption that smaller communities and their
stewards will face greater challenges than larger ones.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Open Source Congress represents more than an annual conference. It
embodies the vision of ongoing collaboration among open source
foundations to address the ecosystem&amp;rsquo;s evolving challenges. The
facilitation of coordination between stewards serves at
least two purposes: bridging cultural and language divides that have
historically fragmented global collaboration, and building the
collective capacity needed to engage effectively with increasingly
complex regulatory environments. While the tension between preserving
open source&amp;rsquo;s creative autonomy and meeting external compliance
requirements will continue to influence the ecosystem&amp;rsquo;s future, the
foundation community&amp;rsquo;s growing expertise in policy advocacy and
standards development positions it increasingly better to navigate
these challenges. The conversations at this year&amp;rsquo;s Congress suggest
that open source&amp;rsquo;s greatest strength, its ability to adapt and evolve
organically, will ultimately enable it to thrive within, rather than
despite, the new regulatory landscape.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Pathways to Cybersecurity: Best Practices in Open Source</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/pathways-to-cybersecurity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/pathways-to-cybersecurity/</guid><description>&lt;p>The European Union’s Cyber Resilience Act (CRA) presents a
watershed moment for the open source ecosystem, imposing
rigorous cybersecurity requirements on products with digital
elements (PDEs) commercialized in the EU. While the regulation
will not fully apply until December 2027, with certain provisions
taking effect earlier, the stakes are enormous—penalties
reaching €15 million or 2.5% of global annual turnover for non-compliance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The regulation’s impact extends beyond documentation and
vulnerability reporting. It fundamentally alters the relationship
between upstream open source projects and downstream commercial
adopters, demanding greater collaboration for sustainable
security maintenance. Neither manufacturers nor stewards
can meet CRA requirements in isolation—manufacturers must
conduct due diligence when integrating open source components,
while stewards must implement and document cybersecurity
policies that facilitate secure development.
The Linux Foundation’s analysis of three flagship projects—Civil
Infrastructure Platform (CIP), Yocto Project, and Zephyr Project—reveals
both the readiness and challenges facing open
source software stewards under the new regulatory framework.
The CRA introduces a novel distinction between commercial
manufacturers who bear primary responsibility for product
compliance, and open source software stewards who develop
and maintain open source software without monetization. This
acknowledges the reality that open source components often
constitute up to 96% of modern software while respecting the
fundamental openness of the development model.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>World of Open Source: Open Source Maturity in Europe</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/oss-europe-2024/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/oss-europe-2024/</guid><description>&lt;p>For the past three years, LF Research has conducted a study on the
adoption, opportunities, and perceptions of open source across
Europe. The trend is clear in 2024: the perceived value of open source
continues to increase in the region, and stakeholders across sectors
and industries can see the importance of investing in it. This year&amp;rsquo;s
report identifies key sectors to channel this investment, the
opportunity for the public sector to embrace open source for digital
public goods, and how regulations are interacting with and responding
to more widespread open source adoption and knowledge. With insights
taken from the 2024 World of Open Source survey and augmented by
interviews with over a dozen experts working in open source, this
report unpacks the current state of open source in Europe and
highlights next steps to improve adoption, understanding, and
regulation for open source as this technological space continues to
mature. Read the report for the full investigation into why open
source has hit a watershed moment in Europe.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Futures of innovation and intellectual property regulation in 2040</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/eu-2024-futures-of-innovation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/eu-2024-futures-of-innovation/</guid><description>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/media/img/futures-of-innovation_hueb36638cea12e205090a0d769dc64272_1145325_34d41abebc57ec25e10d0c7d72699c29.webp 400w,
/media/img/futures-of-innovation_hueb36638cea12e205090a0d769dc64272_1145325_6a8ef3b20cb3381ec6d8b6b3d7f5d137.webp 760w,
/media/img/futures-of-innovation_hueb36638cea12e205090a0d769dc64272_1145325_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/futures-of-innovation_hueb36638cea12e205090a0d769dc64272_1145325_34d41abebc57ec25e10d0c7d72699c29.webp"
width="60%"
height="442"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure></description></item><item><title>Open Source in Europe, there and back again</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2023-06-01-welcome-lf-europe/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2023-06-01-welcome-lf-europe/</guid><description>&lt;p>Open source communities and the software they produce have been at the
centre of most of my professional life. Three years ago, I accepted an
offer from MBition, the Mercedes-Benz infotainment development
subsidiary, to develop their open source strategy and drive horizontal
collaboration on the infotainment functionality in the automotive
industry. Since then I have been on an amazing development journey
culminating in the introduction of the new &lt;a href="https://media.mercedes-benz.com/e-class2023" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mercedes-Benz E
class&lt;/a>, the first model
to feature MBition&amp;rsquo;s next generation infotainment software. While
delivering such an amazing product to market was exhilarating, I have
always found a different joy from working directly in the open source
community. As of today I am excited to announce I am going to be
focusing on community development at &lt;a href="https://linuxfoundation.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Linux Foundation
Europe&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Europe has a special place in the open source community. It is home to
projects like LibreOffice, KDE, as well as to CERN where the web was
invented. Linux started in Scandinavia. But just as importantly, and
besides ecosystem-defining projects like that, there is a culture of
collaboration and community. &lt;a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Software
Heritage&lt;/a> is a great example of
looking beyond &amp;ldquo;scratching your own itch&amp;rdquo; at how software shapes
society. This sense of finding common ground and building community
around it is at the heart of the European project for the last
decades. At Linux Foundation Europe, I want to contribute to the open
source software component of this larger effort.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Concretely, I expect there will be three main stakeholders: industry,
the volunteer open source community and the public sector. All three
share a common interest in innovative, stable, secure open source
projects, especially when they get adopted as software infrastructure
components. However, the three groups also speak different languages
and historically have trouble collaborating. This can be overcome, for
example, by hosting projects like
&lt;a href="https://openwallet.foundation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OpenWallet&lt;/a> that bring regulators and
industry together, but also tackle essential software freedom and
digital sovereignty concerns. Open Source is most successful when it
boils down to &amp;ldquo;show me the code&amp;rdquo; and facilitating contributions from
all interested parties. Identifying prospects for such projects and
building the collaboration between all stakeholders will be the
essence of my work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently, there is a lot of attention on regulatory initiatives that
affect the open source community, like the &lt;a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/library/cyber-resilience-act" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cyber Resilience Act
(CRA)&lt;/a>
or the upcoming &lt;a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EU AI
act&lt;/a>. Working with the European
Commision regulators to ensure that those initiatives support the open
source projects that are the key innovation drivers in those areas
instead of hindering them is an absolute top priority. However, the
bigger picture of facilitating and growing projects that span
industry, volunteer community and European governments should take
centre stage in the longer term. I am looking forward to working on
this European-scale challenge and to the collaboration with all the
involved contributors.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The impact of open source software and hardware on technological independence, competitiveness and innovation in the EU economy</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/eu-impact-of-open-source/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/eu-impact-of-open-source/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The impact of open source software and hardware on technological independence, competitiveness and innovation in the EU economy</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-oss-impact/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-oss-impact/</guid><description>&lt;p>This study analyses the economic impact of Open Source Software (OSS) and Hardware (OSH) on the European economy. It was commissioned by the European Commission’s DG CONNECT. It is estimated that companies located in the EU invested around €1 billion in OSS in 2018, which resulted in an impact on the European economy of between €65 and €95 billion. The analysis estimates a cost-benefit ratio of above 1:4 and predicts that an increase of 10% of OSS contributions would annually generate an additional 0.4% to 0.6% GDP as well as more than 600 additional ICT start-ups in the EU. Case studies reveal that by procuring OSS instead of proprietary software, the public sector could reduce the total cost of ownership, avoid vendor lock-in and thus increase its digital autonomy. The study also contains an analysis of existing public policy actions in Europe and around the world. The scale of Europe’s institutional capacity related to OSS, however, is disproportionately smaller than the scale of the value created by OSS. The study therefore gives a number of specific public policy recommendations aimed at achieving a digitally autonomous public sector, open R&amp;amp;D enabling European growth and a digitised and internally competitive industry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Communication about the study:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>European Commission: &lt;a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/library/study-about-impact-open-source-software-and-hardware-technological-independence-competitiveness-and" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Study about the impact of open source software and hardware on technological independence, competitiveness and innovation in the EU economy&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>OpenForum Europe: &lt;a href="https://openforumeurope.org/publications/study-about-the-impact-of-open-source-software-and-hardware-on-technological-independence-competitiveness-and-innovation-in-the-eu-economy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The study on the impact of Open Source Software and Hardware for the European Commission found that open source software and hardware are key for the region’s digital transformation and can be a major boost to the EU’s GDP&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/eu-impact-of-open-source/">Final study report&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>The Relationship Between Open Source Software and Standard Setting</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/ec-jrc-oss-sdo/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/ec-jrc-oss-sdo/</guid><description>&lt;p>This publication is a Science for Policy report by the Joint Research
Centre (JRC), the European Commission’s science and knowledge
service. It aims to provide evidence-based scientific support to the
European policymaking process. The scientific output expressed does
not imply a policy position of the European Commission. Neither the
European Commission nor any person acting on behalf of the Commission
is responsible for the use that might be made of this publication.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/media/img/publication/_hu37dd48c4b1e0b702c342195a692228d3_709897_167be684a2b19eda746d16451364924d.webp 400w,
/media/img/publication/_hu37dd48c4b1e0b702c342195a692228d3_709897_a2fbee6494e3d063ba67dccea0dd6383.webp 760w,
/media/img/publication/_hu37dd48c4b1e0b702c342195a692228d3_709897_6a0d6270f86beaaeb8111c54c57922a0.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/publication/_hu37dd48c4b1e0b702c342195a692228d3_709897_167be684a2b19eda746d16451364924d.webp"
width="60%"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The report has been developed in the framework of the 2017
Communication of the European Commission ‘Setting out the EU approach
to Standard Essential Patents’ (COM(2017) 712 final). In this
Communication there is a direct commitment that &amp;lsquo;The Commission will
work with stakeholders, open source communities and SDOs for
successful interaction between open source and standardisation, by
means of studies and analyses&amp;rsquo;. Standards and open source development
are both processes widely adopted in the ICT industry to develop
innovative technologies and drive their adoption in the
market. Innovators and policy makers assume that a closer
collaboration between standards and open source software development
would be mutually beneficial. The interaction between the two is
however not yet fully understood, especially with regard to how the
intellectual property regimes applied by these organisations influence
their ability and motivation to cooperate. This study provides a
comprehensive analysis of the interaction between standard development
organisations (SDOs) and open source software (OSS) communities. The
analysis is based on 20 case studies, a survey of stakeholders
involved in SDOs and OSS communities, an expert workshop, and a
comprehensive review of the literature.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>OpenForum Academy Workshop - Exploring Modern Dimensions of Openness</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2019-09-ofa-workshop/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2019 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2019-09-ofa-workshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>The &lt;a href="http://www.openforumeurope.org/about-ofe/openforum-academy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OpenForum
Academy&lt;/a>
held its second 2019 workshop in Brussels this week. OpenForum Academy
is a European-based independent think tank which explains the merits
of openness in computing to policy makers, industry and communities across
Europe. This workshop series aims at being a forum for practitioners,
academics and policy makers to collaborate on various topics of
openness and freedom. It is organized by &lt;a href="http://www.openforumeurope.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OpenForum
Europe&lt;/a>, enabling it to bridge
between the abstract academic world and policy discussions at
the European Commissions. We set out to explore focus topics to answer
current challenges to openness that the academy will develop insights
and recommendations for. These topics will shape the work of
OpenForum Academy for the near future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The workshop was opened by a series of input presentations. One of
those was on &amp;ldquo;Addressing lock-in challenges through the use of open
source software projects&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href="https://www.his.se/en/about-us/Facts-and-figures/staff/bjorn_lundell/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Björn
Lundell&lt;/a>,
a fellow of the academy and professor at the University of Skövde in
Sweden. He explained for example the need for open source solutions to
read and write data formats of digital assets of long-term
importance.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-standard-and-file-format-lock-in">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Standard and File Format Lock-In" srcset="
/media/img/post/2019-09-10_Lundell_OFA-workshop_Brussels_Slide4_hu8d291b392dc10072f966ead193d17207_756001_dcd68d2df68f540c1b1f3a30e5b163b6.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2019-09-10_Lundell_OFA-workshop_Brussels_Slide4_hu8d291b392dc10072f966ead193d17207_756001_b9efb7bc56e5d3159ad9136f1fedd29e.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2019-09-10_Lundell_OFA-workshop_Brussels_Slide4_hu8d291b392dc10072f966ead193d17207_756001_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2019-09-10_Lundell_OFA-workshop_Brussels_Slide4_hu8d291b392dc10072f966ead193d17207_756001_dcd68d2df68f540c1b1f3a30e5b163b6.webp"
width="60%"
height="428"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Standard and File Format Lock-In
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I presented key findings and recommendations from the
study on &lt;a href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/">&amp;ldquo;The Role of Open Source Software in Standard Setting&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>. All this served to frame the following
discussion of potential core topics for the OpenForum Academy to focus.
OpenForum Europe champions openness in Europe, a topic that has
sprawled into numerous debates. Which ones of those are important and
warrant the development of academic papers and policy briefs?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="OpenForum Academy workshop attendees" srcset="
/media/img/post/2019-09-OFA-workshop_hu8e638188a6937bd07708cddf65e33c5a_503509_6222910029fc230ca872a420ba777c1c.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2019-09-OFA-workshop_hu8e638188a6937bd07708cddf65e33c5a_503509_4b0df9a52e790f2a176498125fb85038.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2019-09-OFA-workshop_hu8e638188a6937bd07708cddf65e33c5a_503509_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2019-09-OFA-workshop_hu8e638188a6937bd07708cddf65e33c5a_503509_6222910029fc230ca872a420ba777c1c.webp"
width="60%"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="exploring-modern-dimensions-of-openness">Exploring modern dimensions of openness&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Personally, I am primarily interested in Open Source aspects. However,
there are other dimensions of openness that cover different processes
and results. There is still a discussion of what an &lt;em>open standard&lt;/em>
is. &lt;em>Open hardware&lt;/em> works quite differently to software, because the
open specifications eventually have to be turned into physical
goods. Access to data is an angle independent from software,
specifications and hardware, and most software is made useful by the data
sets it processes. We want more scientific articles to be
available under &lt;em>open access&lt;/em> licenses, especially when they are
creating with public funding. The list of topics related to openness
is probably never-ending. Eventually, the following aspects emerged
as the currently most interesting ones:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="openness-and-the-cloud">Openness and the Cloud&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>How the transition of ICT to cloud and edge services changes the
importance of FOSS and data unsurprisingly sparked a heated debate
during the workshop. Is software freedom threatened by the rise of
cloud computing because software modifications are not required to be
shared? How can vendor lock-in and a lack of choice be overcome? Very
importantly, what is new about cloud that is different to before
(hint: it may be less than we think)? How can consumer interests be
protected and a healthy business ecosystem promoted? How can
regulation help and where does regulation overreach (think
surveillance or user profiling)? Many of these questions are about
finding the right balance, or identifying the justified intrusions
into the user&amp;rsquo;s rights to confidentiality and privacy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="open-source-as-civil-ict-infrastructure">Open Source as Civil ICT Infrastructure&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The EU invests in railroads, highways and data networks. Why does it
not invest much into
FOSS? &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/eusurvey/runner/EUFOSSA2-Survey" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FOSSA&lt;/a>
(hint: please participate in the survey!) is a good start. Much more
could be done. Civil society is stepping in to take over public
functions, as in the preservation of knowledge fostered by Wikipedia
or Software Heritage, often with little public support. What would be
a framework under which the EU and member states can invest into FOSS
development, to serve it&amp;rsquo;s own needs or to support support
sustainability goals? Can a public investment plan be developed for
the development of OSS ICT infrastructure, including goals and spends?&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="commercial-business-models-and-open-source">Commercial Business Models and Open Source&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Much has been discussed recently about the sustainability of FOSS
development, often confusing it the viability of the own business
model. Norms that form the pillars of the FOSS movement like
the
&lt;a href="https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/basics/4freedoms.en.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">four freedoms of software&lt;/a> or
the &lt;a href="https://opensource.org/osd" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Source Definition&lt;/a> embody
community culture at the expense of legalistic terminology. Recently,
models have emerged that remove some of the freedoms guaranteed by
those norms, for example in the deceptively
named &lt;a href="https://commonsclause.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Commons Clause License&lt;/a>. The
relation between FOSS and other rights like trademarks or patents is
still a much researched topic. Directly related to that are approaches
on how to valuate FOSS and FOSS based businesses to give guidance to
industry, VCs and policy makers for investment decisions. Some of our
fellows feel it is important to take a stand as a community, insist on
making it clear what FOSS really is and prevent a watering down of
standards like the Open Source Definition. There is a need to explain
the work of the wider FOSS community more clearly to illustrate how it
interacts with and contributes to society.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-to-contribute-and-get-involved">How to contribute and get involved&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The academy believes that these topic are of wide-ranging importance
to the development of the digital society and the single market in the
EU. They warrant a thorough investigation, deep analysis and a search
for solutions that connects research, industry and policy makers. We
hope to support this process by selecting these three subjects as
focus topics for the OpenForum Academy for the upcoming year. The
academy will facilitate the work of it&amp;rsquo;s fellows through workshops,
publications and other means. If you are a researcher, practitioner,
engaged in European politics or simply otherwise interested, follow
&lt;em>@OpenForumEurope&lt;/em> or
&lt;a href="http://www.openforumeurope.org/about-ofe/openforum-academy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">contact&lt;/a>
OpenForum Academy to get involved.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Gamalielsson, J. &amp;amp; Lundell, B. (2013) Experiences from implementing PDF in open source: challenges and opportunities for standardisation processes, In Jakobs, K. (Ed.) Proceedings of the 8th IEEE Conference on Standardization and Innovation in Information Technology (SIIT 2013), ISBN 3-86130-802-9, IEEE, Piscataway, pp. 39-49. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/SIIT.2013.6774572" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1109/SIIT.2013.6774572&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>FOSS, standard essential patents and FRAND in the European Union</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2018-jrc-workshop/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2018-jrc-workshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of the research project
on
&lt;a href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/">&amp;ldquo;The Interaction between Open Source Software and FRAND licensing in Standardisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>,
a workshop was organised by the European Commission, Joint Research
Centre (JRC) in collaboration with Directorate General Communications
Networks, Content and Technology (CONNECT) to present and discuss the
intermediate results to date. The workshop took place in Brussels on
September 18, 2018. I presented a set of observations from the research on
the case studies performed as part of the project that are outlined
below. Other speakers
where
&lt;a href="https://www.the-klu.org/faculty-research/resident-faculty/catharina-maracke/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Catharina Maracke&lt;/a> on
the issue of legal compliance between Open Source and FRAND
licenses, &lt;a href="https://perens.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bruce Perens&lt;/a> on &amp;ldquo;Community Dynamics
in Open Source&amp;rdquo;,
and &lt;a href="https://www.gesmer.com/team/andrew-s-updegrove" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Andy Updegrove&lt;/a>
on &amp;ldquo;Dynamics in Standardisation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You may ask what the relevance of this debate is for the wider Free
and Open Source Software community. The obvious answer is that to
distribute
software
&lt;a href="https://opensource.com/article/18/3/patent-grant-mit-license" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;without restriction&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>,
the user needs all the usage rights associated with the program. While
most FOSS contributors assume that this is naturally the central
motivation for anybody to contribute in the first place, there is a
long history of attempts to maintain some sort of exclusive control
over a piece of FOSS code, possibly using other rights than copyright.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Contributor license agreements (CLA) are a well known instrument for
that. The original author agrees to an exclusive or non-exclusive
license to a central entity (usually a community organisation or a
dominating company) to use their work. This may just give a community
organisation a right to adopt newer licenses. Or it may give
a
&lt;a href="https://dirkriehle.com/publications/2009-selected/the-commercial-open-source-business-model/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">single Open Source vendor&lt;/a> the
right to use other contributor&amp;rsquo;s work commercially. Whether CLA embody
FOSS culture or violate them by creating an asymmetric distribution of
benefits between contributors and a company therefore depends on the
specific terms of the
CLA. The
&lt;a href="http://contributoragreements.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">contributor agreements configurator&lt;/a> helps
projects to set up a CLA and understand what the motivation behind the
terms are (&lt;a href="https://endocode.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Endocode&lt;/a> contributed the
implementation). CLA are controversial, especially if they
include
&lt;a href="https://help.nextcloud.com/t/cla-caa-ca-etc-etc-let-s-get-it-right/588" target="_blank" rel="noopener">copyright assignments to a single company&lt;/a>. Projects
and contributors are well-advised to make sure to fully understand
what they are agreeing to. The main take-away for the argument here is
that the norm in FOSS communities is a &lt;em>symmetric&lt;/em> distribution of
rights between all contributors, and CLA are one instrument to modify
this to the benefit of a single entity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But that is not all. It just helps to explain how such asymmetric
rights can be used to give a single entity more power in a community
of contributors. There is a long history of such attempts, and they
usually involve some other legal rights beyond the terms of the FOSS
license applied. There is a good reason for that: FOSS licenses give
contributors and users a time-tested and well-balanced framework for
collaboration. &lt;a href="https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/basics/4freedoms.en.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;Use, study, modify, redistribute&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> is
a simple, easy to understand mantra that every FOSS contributor knows
and understands. CLA augment the FOSS license terms with an additional
contractual agreement, but for the most part stay in the realm of
copyright just like FOSS licenses. Other instruments not so much:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Trademarks are used to enforce a vendor&amp;rsquo;s expectations when others
adopt and ship their software. This is used by communities to
protect their names, like in
the
&lt;a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/foundation/trademarks/policy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mozilla Trademark Policy&lt;/a>,
or to make sure specific services are included in devices, like in
the
&lt;a href="https://source.android.com/compatibility/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Android Compatibility Program&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Trade secrets like delayed code releases under FOSS licenses or
proprietary &amp;ldquo;extensions&amp;rdquo; that
are
&lt;a href="https://about.mattermost.com/features/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">effectively required for the software to be useful&lt;/a> are
used to maintain an edge of an &amp;ldquo;enterprise&amp;rdquo; version over the FOSS
release.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The
&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/software-patents.en.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">software patents debate&lt;/a> may
have slowed down, but is still relevant. Patents exist, and
applications for patents that include claims that are implemented in
existing FOSS solutions never stopped. It has become harder to be
granted a patent for a software-only solution. Institutions like
the &lt;a href="https://www.openinventionnetwork.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Invention Network&lt;/a>
create a safe space where FOSS innovators cross-license freely and
avoid litigation. However vendors shipping FOSS in products still
need to clear potential patent claims implemented in
those. Conformance with patents does not usually follow from FOSS
licenses.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Which leads to round five of the match with software freedom in one
corner and exclusivity in the other &amp;ndash; standard-essential patents
(SEP). Everybody loves standards, and FOSS especially: We use
standardised programming languages, unicode tables and system call
interfaces. Standards are the foundation for interoperability, and
some standards like
the &lt;a href="http://opendocumentformat.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Document Format&lt;/a> are the
result of a long struggle to establish formats that re-open markets
for competition. All of these standards
are
&lt;a href="https://opensource.com/resources/what-are-open-standards" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Standards&lt;/a> that
can be implemented in FOSS without restrictions. But what if
implementing a standard would be required to interoperate with others,
or even mandatory under existing regulations, and this standard would
include functionality that is covered by patent claims, possibly with
royalty-bearing patent licenses? That is the definition of SEP, which
are commonly required to be licensed either royalty-free or under
&amp;ldquo;fair, reasonable and non-discriminatory&amp;rdquo; (FRAND) licenses. It is also
a relevant and current concern because
the
&lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/docsroom/documents/26583" target="_blank" rel="noopener">European Commission considers SEP under FRAND licenses a useful instrument&lt;/a> for
industrial policy in the European Union. Until now, the wider FOSS
community has contributed some positions to this debate that is for
the most part dominated by incumbent industries, recognized
standards-development organisations (SDO) and policy makers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The study currently conducted under the supervision by
the
&lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/departments/joint-research-centre_en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">European Commission Joint Research Centre (EC-JRC)&lt;/a> on
&lt;a href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/">&amp;ldquo;The Interaction between Open Source Software and FRAND licensing in Standardisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> aims
at providing a better understanding of the interplay between FOSS
licenses, governance and the IPR policies of SDO. At the workshop that
was just held in Brussels as part of this study where an initial set
of case studies on the subject have been presented. Theses case
studies (that I am the author of) will become part of the overall
study report prepared
by
&lt;a href="https://www.inno.tu-berlin.de/menue/about_us/team/prof_dr_rer_pol/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Knut Blind&lt;/a> and
me. As the study progresses, a number of early observations from these
cases will be shared in this blog and other channels. It is important
that the wider FOSS community recognizes the relevance and importance
of this subject and actively makes itself heard. CERN, the ECMAscript
community, the Eclipse Foundation, the Linux Foundation and others
have already contributed insights to the field work for the
project. Others, especially FSFE, have been notably absent from the
debate. The &lt;a href="https://opensource.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Source Initiative&lt;/a> is
represented on the project&amp;rsquo;s steering committee.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The standards that
will be shaped by this debate, like 5G mobile communication or IoT
protocols, will affect us all, as will welfare gains or losses from
policies that influence the innovativeness of FOSS. There are
opportunities to contribute: communities can communicate what their
needs are with regards to standards and FOSS. Contributors can
provide input to the case studies or the stakeholder survey that will
be performed in the next phase of the study. Feel free to reach out if
you would like to participate.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Relationship Between Open Source Software and Standard Setting</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/</guid><description>&lt;p>The objective of the study is to identify possible commonalities and
barriers for interaction between standardisation and open source
processes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The study should clarify the role of open source in the context of
standard setting, in particular its interplay with the licensing of
standards-essential patents under &amp;ldquo;fair, reasonable and
non-discriminatory&amp;rdquo; (FRAND) terms and provide an overview of free and
open source software (FOSS) and FRAND features in standardisation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The study on the interaction between open source software and FRAND
licensing in standardisation is carried out on behalf of the &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/departments/joint-research-centre_en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">European
Commission&amp;rsquo;s Joint Research
Centre&lt;/a>
by &lt;a href="https://www.fokus.fraunhofer.de/en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fraunhofer Institute of Open Communication System
FOKUS&lt;/a> and Mirko Böhm representing
the &lt;a href="https://www.openinventionnetwork.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Invention Network&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Communication about the study:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>European Commission: &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/news/study-role-open-source-standard-setting" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Study on the role of open source in standard setting&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>EU Science Hub: &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/jrc/en/science-update/jrc-study-interaction-between-open-source-software-and-frand-licensing-standardisation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">JRC Study on the Interaction between Open Source Software and FRAND licensing in Standardisation&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Publication of the final report: &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/jrc/en/publication/eur-scientific-and-technical-research-reports/relationship-between-open-source-software-and-standard-setting" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Relationship Between Open Source Software and Standard Setting&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The project was originally named &amp;ldquo;The Interaction between Open Source
Software and FRAND licensing in Standardisation&amp;rdquo;. The title was later
simplified to &amp;ldquo;The Relationship Between Open Source Software and
Standard Setting&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ist Open Source demokratisch?</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/jahrbuch-netzpolitik-2012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/jahrbuch-netzpolitik-2012/</guid><description>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/media/img/publication/npjahresbuch_cover_hua2e4f8e33ebb3f859d810ac5d8c3facd_49089_e98c72b5dbd09c9798dd9ff862748fce.webp 400w,
/media/img/publication/npjahresbuch_cover_hua2e4f8e33ebb3f859d810ac5d8c3facd_49089_782b12d81404ef6332a2d3db45056a44.webp 760w,
/media/img/publication/npjahresbuch_cover_hua2e4f8e33ebb3f859d810ac5d8c3facd_49089_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/publication/npjahresbuch_cover_hua2e4f8e33ebb3f859d810ac5d8c3facd_49089_e98c72b5dbd09c9798dd9ff862748fce.webp"
width="60%"
height="759"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Open-Source-Communities gelten als selbstgesteuert, meritokratisch et
cetera, aber ein besonderer demokratischer Charakter ihres
Funktionierens steht selten im Vordergrund. Einzelne investieren oft
großen Aufwand in ihr Lieblingsprojekt, um zu einem größeren Ganzen
beizutragen, und Demokratie gilt ebenfalls oft als höheres Gut. Es ist
daher verlockend, vom einen aufs andere zu schließen und
Open-Source-Communities ebenfalls als grundsätzlich demokratisch
anzunehmen. Aber ist das wirklich der Fall? Was bedeutet Demokratie im
Kontext von Open Source eigentlich? Wie würde eine demokratische
Open-Source-Community aussehen?&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>