<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>personal | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/personal/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>personal</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>personal</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/personal/</link></image><item><title>Open Source in Europe, there and back again</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2023-06-01-welcome-lf-europe/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2023-06-01-welcome-lf-europe/</guid><description>&lt;p>Open source communities and the software they produce have been at the
centre of most of my professional life. Three years ago, I accepted an
offer from MBition, the Mercedes-Benz infotainment development
subsidiary, to develop their open source strategy and drive horizontal
collaboration on the infotainment functionality in the automotive
industry. Since then I have been on an amazing development journey
culminating in the introduction of the new &lt;a href="https://media.mercedes-benz.com/e-class2023" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mercedes-Benz E
class&lt;/a>, the first model
to feature MBition&amp;rsquo;s next generation infotainment software. While
delivering such an amazing product to market was exhilarating, I have
always found a different joy from working directly in the open source
community. As of today I am excited to announce I am going to be
focusing on community development at &lt;a href="https://linuxfoundation.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Linux Foundation
Europe&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Europe has a special place in the open source community. It is home to
projects like LibreOffice, KDE, as well as to CERN where the web was
invented. Linux started in Scandinavia. But just as importantly, and
besides ecosystem-defining projects like that, there is a culture of
collaboration and community. &lt;a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Software
Heritage&lt;/a> is a great example of
looking beyond &amp;ldquo;scratching your own itch&amp;rdquo; at how software shapes
society. This sense of finding common ground and building community
around it is at the heart of the European project for the last
decades. At Linux Foundation Europe, I want to contribute to the open
source software component of this larger effort.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Concretely, I expect there will be three main stakeholders: industry,
the volunteer open source community and the public sector. All three
share a common interest in innovative, stable, secure open source
projects, especially when they get adopted as software infrastructure
components. However, the three groups also speak different languages
and historically have trouble collaborating. This can be overcome, for
example, by hosting projects like
&lt;a href="https://openwallet.foundation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OpenWallet&lt;/a> that bring regulators and
industry together, but also tackle essential software freedom and
digital sovereignty concerns. Open Source is most successful when it
boils down to &amp;ldquo;show me the code&amp;rdquo; and facilitating contributions from
all interested parties. Identifying prospects for such projects and
building the collaboration between all stakeholders will be the
essence of my work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently, there is a lot of attention on regulatory initiatives that
affect the open source community, like the &lt;a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/library/cyber-resilience-act" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cyber Resilience Act
(CRA)&lt;/a>
or the upcoming &lt;a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EU AI
act&lt;/a>. Working with the European
Commision regulators to ensure that those initiatives support the open
source projects that are the key innovation drivers in those areas
instead of hindering them is an absolute top priority. However, the
bigger picture of facilitating and growing projects that span
industry, volunteer community and European governments should take
centre stage in the longer term. I am looking forward to working on
this European-scale challenge and to the collaboration with all the
involved contributors.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>