<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>governance | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/governance/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/governance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>governance</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>governance</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/governance/</link></image><item><title>Open Source Congress 2025</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2025-09-16-open-source-congress/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2025-09-16-open-source-congress/</guid><description>&lt;p>The third &lt;a href="https://www.opensourcecongress.org/event/2025/open-source-congress-2025" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Source
Congress&lt;/a>
took place in Brussels on 16 September 2025. This annual gathering
brings together code-hosting open source foundations and partners to
align on critical issues facing the ecosystem. After the Linux
Foundation created Open Source Congress in 2023, each year a different
organization has signed up as the host. I would like to thank the
Eclipse Foundation for agreeing to be the host this year. The event
focused on four key topics: open source in a multi-polar world,
cybersecurity, sustainability, and regulation and public policy. The
primary value of such gatherings lies in alignment and exchange rather
than concrete actions. Since Open Source Congress operates under
Chatham House rules and is less accessible than typical open source
events, sharing insights from the discussions serves the wider
community. Below are personal observations from the four panels.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="panel-1---open-source-in-a-multi-polar-world">Panel 1 - Open Source in a Multi-Polar World&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The open source ecosystem was multi-polar from its inception. Key open
source innovations originate from various regions: Ruby from
Japan, Linux and Python from Europe, the GNU Project from the US. The
US tech industry was quicker to realize open source technologies as
a growth driver, allowing US business interests to overlay this
narrative today. However, nothing is inherently polarizing in how the
open source ecosystem works. It serves as both
creative destruction and resilience mechanism, undermining
traditional control structures while remaining largely
unregulable. Cultural and language barriers continue to shape
how and where contributors collaborate, making truly global
collaboration a key challenge. There is optimism
that AI will provide instant translation mechanisms to bridge
such divides. Maintaining arms-length distance from policy making
remains essential to preserve open source&amp;rsquo;s organic governance. At the same
time, regulation will inevitably affect the
ecosystem&amp;rsquo;s global dynamics. The EU Cyber Resilience Act is
the first law explicitly shaping stakeholder roles.
While progress has been made in building capacity and
expertise for open source foundations to engage in policy debates
when necessary, much work remains.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="panel-2---cybersecurity-influencing-best-practices-and-standards">Panel 2 - Cybersecurity: Influencing Best Practices and Standards&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A global race to define cybersecurity standards creates a
maze of regulation across international markets. While this
challenges global manufacturers, open source communities face few
concrete regulatory obligations. However, to enable global adoption of their
releases, they are strongly incentivized to support
downstream users with documentation and sound cybersecurity
practices. Creating an environment conducive to smooth
upstream-downstream collaboration requires open source foundations to
engage in relevant standards development processes that define
implementation details of cybersecurity regulation. This
remains difficult, as most stewards lack both funding and
subject matter expertise for standards development.
The panel revealed tensions between traditional open source
collaboration and emerging bureaucratic frameworks at organizations
like the
&lt;a href="https://unite.un.org/en/news/sixteen-organizations-endorse-un-open-source-principles" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UN&lt;/a>
and &lt;a href="https://www.digitalpublicgoods.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DPGA&lt;/a>, warning that OSS
risks losing its core strengths when bent to external rules. The
discussion emphasized that effective policy engagement should
facilitate organic collaboration and create market-driven incentives
rather than impose rigid bureaucratic structures. Initiatives like
the Linux Foundation&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://alpha-omega.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alpha-Omega&lt;/a> serve as
effective funding instruments that align with open source
principles. In recent years, public initiatives like the German
&lt;a href="https://www.sovereign.tech/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sovereign Tech Agency&lt;/a> increasingly
support under-maintained projects. Under guidance from &lt;a href="https://openforumeurope.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Forum
Europe&lt;/a>, a &lt;a href="https://eu-stf.openforumeurope.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">feasibility
study&lt;/a> has been submitted to the
EU to elevate such activities to the European level with a larger
budget.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="panel-3---sustainability-and-the-open-ecosystem">Panel 3 - Sustainability and the Open Ecosystem&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The sustainability of the open source development model is hotly
debated. The underlying issue appears to be a mix of insufficient funding and a
fundamental &amp;ldquo;matchmaking problem&amp;rdquo; of allocating available funds to
specific projects and contributors efficiently. While
the myth that open source is the unpaid labor of love of hobbyist
maintainers still percolates, the 2024 &lt;a href="https://opensourcefundingsurvey2024.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Source Software Funding
Survey&lt;/a> shows that 86% of
contribution value comes from employee labor. This study raises challenging
questions. On one hand, what will be the effect of 50m€ public funding
initiatives if $7.7B is invested by private industry
annually? On the other hand, if more funding becomes available, how
will it be distributed? Grant making will profoundly impact
the viability of individual projects, raising concerns about
public sector actors&amp;rsquo; ability to effectively disperse
sovereign-tech-fund-like funds where they are needed most, rather
than to favored champions or consultancies specializing in grant
acquisition. However, such initiatives will likely support
ecosystem diversity and grassroots initiatives, which may
be a benefit worth the cost.
Some funding programs focus on maintenance or security, creating
a risk of fragmenting development work by separating improvement,
maintenance, and security responsibilities. Since implementing new
features is always most fascinating, the impression that maintenance
and cybersecurity are somebody else&amp;rsquo;s problem must be avoided.
Emerging models favor market-driven approaches like
the EU CRA, which creates business incentives for maintenance work and
eliminates freeloading, potentially contributing more to
open source sustainability than public spending programs that struggle
with coordination and measurement challenges.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="panel-4---regulation-and-public-policy">Panel 4 - Regulation and Public Policy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The final session was essentially a moderated Q&amp;amp;A round. A cluster of
questions evolved around how external forces now influencing the open
source world will reshape open collaboration dynamics. The
release-early-release-often, show-me-the-code mentality drives
experimentation and a somewhat Darwinian trial-and-error approach to
identifying promising projects. Voluntary participation ensures that
projects receive attention according to their value to the
community. Interestingly, funding programs based on selective awards
are expected to bias these mechanisms more than market access
regulation. Future research is needed to verify this expectation.
However, regulatory approaches will fundamentally reshape the
ecosystem by influencing adoption criteria for components, driving
consolidation of fragmented libraries into fewer, more maintainable
packages and addressing collective action problems around
responsibility and decision-making in policy advocacy. This will
affect different communities differently, depending on factors like the
granularity and maintainer base of package repositories. However, there
is a prevailing assumption that smaller communities and their
stewards will face greater challenges than larger ones.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Open Source Congress represents more than an annual conference. It
embodies the vision of ongoing collaboration among open source
foundations to address the ecosystem&amp;rsquo;s evolving challenges. The
facilitation of coordination between stewards serves at
least two purposes: bridging cultural and language divides that have
historically fragmented global collaboration, and building the
collective capacity needed to engage effectively with increasingly
complex regulatory environments. While the tension between preserving
open source&amp;rsquo;s creative autonomy and meeting external compliance
requirements will continue to influence the ecosystem&amp;rsquo;s future, the
foundation community&amp;rsquo;s growing expertise in policy advocacy and
standards development positions it increasingly better to navigate
these challenges. The conversations at this year&amp;rsquo;s Congress suggest
that open source&amp;rsquo;s greatest strength, its ability to adapt and evolve
organically, will ultimately enable it to thrive within, rather than
despite, the new regulatory landscape.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The place of the open source ecosystem in the innovation landscape</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/the-place-of-open-source/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/the-place-of-open-source/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Economics of Open Source</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/oup-economics-of-open-source/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/oup-economics-of-open-source/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Open Source Software in Standard Setting: The Role of Intellectual Property Right Regimes</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/oup-open-source-standards/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/oup-open-source-standards/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Standard setting organizations and open source communities: Partners or competitors?</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/ssofoss-en/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/ssofoss-en/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Opinions and facts</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2017-03-16-opinions-and-facts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2017-03-16-opinions-and-facts/</guid><description>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Opinions and facts" srcset="
/media/img/post/2017-03-opinions-and-facts_huc73dc40a0021abba3da9ebc30bcd1f21_13841_274e850b894d43f673bca296b316d40f.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2017-03-opinions-and-facts_huc73dc40a0021abba3da9ebc30bcd1f21_13841_d6d5a5257af09ed9679dda1660644f5c.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2017-03-opinions-and-facts_huc73dc40a0021abba3da9ebc30bcd1f21_13841_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2017-03-opinions-and-facts_huc73dc40a0021abba3da9ebc30bcd1f21_13841_274e850b894d43f673bca296b316d40f.webp"
width="80%"
height="380"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="from-the-economist-espresso-quote-of-the-day">From The Economist Espresso: Quote of the day&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>For a long time I was looking for a source for this quote. Separating
facts and opinions provides a good foundation for many debates. Be
wary, though, when applying it to discussions with the significant
other ;-)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Claim the right not to tolerate the intolerant</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2015-12-08-dont-tolerate-the-intolerant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2015-12-08-dont-tolerate-the-intolerant/</guid><description>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Claim the right not to tolerate the intolerant" srcset="
/media/img/post/2015-12-popper_hu574f1a1ff4dfacf96c6deebc86c6e16e_22183_fa673ec4afcfa45beadd457d3f481e46.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2015-12-popper_hu574f1a1ff4dfacf96c6deebc86c6e16e_22183_d9d337e4ab3af315c4c4d5fc4fc8673d.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2015-12-popper_hu574f1a1ff4dfacf96c6deebc86c6e16e_22183_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2015-12-popper_hu574f1a1ff4dfacf96c6deebc86c6e16e_22183_fa673ec4afcfa45beadd457d3f481e46.webp"
width="80%"
height="380"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="from-the-economist-espresso-quote-of-the-day">From The Economist Espresso: Quote of the day&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Karl Popper is one of my heroes. His &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Open_Society_and_Its_Enemies" target="_blank" rel="noopener">thoughts on the &amp;ldquo;open
society&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>
are one of the most influential books I read while studying
at university (and again, recently). It shaped my thinking about
political systems like few others. Not to mention &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Logic_of_Scientific_Discovery" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;The Logic of
Scientific
Discovery&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>,
another book by him that feels like a revelation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>'Open Source in Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft' an der Sommeruni 2013 des evangelischen Studienwerks</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-09-15-sommeruni/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2013 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-09-15-sommeruni/</guid><description>&lt;p>Jedes Jahr wieder findet die Sommeruni des evangelischen Studienwerks
statt. In diesem Jahr mit dabei war das Seminar &lt;a href="http://www.evstudienwerk.de/aktuelles/veranstaltungen/sommeruniversitaet/65.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Source in
Wirtschaft und
Gesellschaft&lt;/a>
von Mirko Boehm. Paul Adams unterstützte als Ko-Referent. Karsten
Gerloff, Präsident der &lt;a href="http://fsfe.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FSFE&lt;/a>, trat als Gastredner
auf. Da sich die Teilnehmer ihre Seminare nach eigenem Interesse
selbst aussuchen, fand sich ein bunte Mischung von Medizinern über
Naturwissenschaftlern bis zu Theologen zusammen. Die Verbindung aus
Neugier, Heterogenität der Gruppe und inspirierender Umgebung sorgte
für explosive Debatten, hitzige Diskussionsrunden und eine wie Flug
vergangene Woche.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Schwerpunkte des Seminars waren die Fragen, wie
Open-Source-Communities eigentlich funktionieren, was Einzelne zur
Mitwirkung motiviert, wie sich freie Produkte in die
Wirtschaftsordnung integrieren und welche politischen
Herausforderungen und Veränderungen zu bewältigen sind. Während
schnell Einverständnis herrschte darüber, das der &lt;em>Open Source Way&lt;/em>
ein gesellschaftliches und kein technisches Problem ist, wurde zu
anderen sonst in der
&lt;a href="http://saschalobo.com/2013/03/22/unsere-muetter-unsere-fehler/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Netzgemeinde&lt;/a>
als selbstverständlich vermutete Ansichten wie &amp;ldquo;das Internet gehört
den Benutzern&amp;rdquo; gut argumentiert hinterfragt. Wer trägt die
Verantwortung für durch unvorsichtige Bewertungen beschädigte
Reputation, muss alle Teilhabe in Zukunft im Netz stattfinden, braucht
es eine Internetpolizei, das Strafrecht der realen Welt erweiternde
Sanktionen, die Regulierung des Netzes? Durch die diversen Blickwinkel
war manchmal nicht klar, wer mehr von wem lernte, die Seminarleitung
oder die Teilnehmer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Karsten Gerloff berichtete über die politische Bedeutung von Freier
Software und offener Innovation, die Bedrohung durch Softwarepatente
und die Kampagnenarbeit der FSFE.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-paul-karsten-und-mirko-bei-der-sommeruni">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Paul, Karsten und Mirko bei der Sommeruni" srcset="
/media/img/post/2013-09-sommeruni_hu8943cc80b8385487f1fe7baba6e98aa2_1806199_378ae289f2109b404a7ffe34c3079b52.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2013-09-sommeruni_hu8943cc80b8385487f1fe7baba6e98aa2_1806199_671511a25c6ae08b5f540f81e786cfb3.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2013-09-sommeruni_hu8943cc80b8385487f1fe7baba6e98aa2_1806199_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2013-09-sommeruni_hu8943cc80b8385487f1fe7baba6e98aa2_1806199_378ae289f2109b404a7ffe34c3079b52.webp"
width="80%"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Paul, Karsten und Mirko bei der Sommeruni
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Die Beschäftigung mit der Materie war dabei von deutlicher
Ernsthaftigkeit geprägt. Zum Beispiel brauchten die Teilnehmer etwa
fünf Minuten, um den systematischen Unterschied bei der Integration
von Copyleft- oder Permissive-lizensierten Beiträgen zu verstehen -
ein Prozess, der bei nicht wenigen Freie-Software-Communities entweder
gar nicht oder erst recht spät verstanden wird. Paul Adams war
sichtlich beeindruckt. Dieses tiefe Eintauchen ins Thema steht
beispielhaft für das allgemein starke Engagement der Stipendiaten, die
ihr Studienwerk in weiten Bereichen selbst verwalten - bis hin zur
Zusammenstellung des Programms der Sommeruniversität selbst.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bei der traditionell turbulenten Abschlussveranstaltung am
Donnerstagabend wurden die &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Free_Software_Definition" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Vier
Freiheiten&lt;/a>
anhand der kollaborativen Beschwörung des Geists von Villigst
illustriert - wenn das nicht eine erfolgreiche Wissensvermittlung
verdeutlicht&amp;hellip; Unser einstimmiges Fazit - definitiv eine Woche
lohnend investierter Zeit, die Paul Adams und ich in guter Erinnerung
behalten werden. Neben den Teilnehmern war auch das Organisationsteam
(ebenfalls sich freiwillig engagierende Stipendiaten) ausgesprochen
engagiert und sorgte für einen reibungslosen, angenehmen Ablauf von
insgesamt sechs parallel verlaufenden Seminaren. Sehr beeindruckend.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>KDE e.V. General Assembly 2013</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-07-18-kde-ga/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-07-18-kde-ga/</guid><description>&lt;p>tl;dr: If you are a committed KDE contributor and not a KDE
e.V. member, you are doing it wrong. If you are a KDE user, consider
helping the KDE User Working Group. Read KDE e.V.&amp;rsquo;s quarterly reports.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-the-test-vote-before-the-assembly-officially-started">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Voting at the KDE e.V. general assembly" srcset="
/media/img/post/2013-07-kde-ga_huaf89183451818f046cfc9b11bff581d8_1476085_59c65bc2fa97e3e30486b67fc3148ef0.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2013-07-kde-ga_huaf89183451818f046cfc9b11bff581d8_1476085_451dd665076a0028479e0da93df2de63.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2013-07-kde-ga_huaf89183451818f046cfc9b11bff581d8_1476085_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2013-07-kde-ga_huaf89183451818f046cfc9b11bff581d8_1476085_59c65bc2fa97e3e30486b67fc3148ef0.webp"
width="80%"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
The test vote before the assembly officially started
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://akademy2013.kde.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Akademy 2013&lt;/a> is still on its way, and as
usual the KDE e.V. General Assembly was held as a part of it. KDE
e.V. is the representation and governance body of the KDE
community. Membership in this not-for-profit association registered in
Berlin, Germany is open to all KDE contributors . Members usually
assemble once a year to coordinate, to vote on issues important to the
community and to elect representatives and board members as
needed. The highlights this year where the discussion of the role of
the Community Working Group, the report on the first activities of the
newly established Financial Working Group, and the election of one
new board member. I was the chairperson of the assembly, and this is
my inofficial report.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The role of KDE e.V. is somewhat described by &amp;ldquo;standing on the
shoulders of giants&amp;rdquo;. It is made up by community members interested
in governance matters, and represents the wider KDE community that
encompasses all non-technical and technical contributors. On one hand
KDE e.V. takes a passive stance, in that it does not directly
influence the direction the development of KDE is taking. On the other
hand it plays an important role and invariably influences the
community by receicing donations, managing funding of development
sprints and meetings, covering operational costs like hardware and
infrastructure, and of course by running the Akademy conference year
after year. This setup is reflected in the working groups that act as
focal points for various fields of interest within the
community. Working groups as established for marketing, system
administration, community, user relations and finance. Notably absent
is a development working group, it is commonly accepted that this is
not KDE e.V.&amp;rsquo;s concern. The membership elects a five person board that
coordinates the work of the KDE e.V. members and the working
groups. KDE e.V. currently has 169 active members, which is an
impressive number considering it&amp;rsquo;s non-technical focus in a
development community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The abbreviation &amp;ldquo;e.V.&amp;rdquo; stands for &amp;ldquo;eingetragener Verein&amp;rdquo;, German for
&amp;ldquo;registered association&amp;rdquo;. It functions much like a shareholders
company in which every member holds exactly one share. This means the
membership as a whole is the proprietor of all assets owned by the KDE
community, including the KDE trademark and the operational
infrastructure. A new member joins the group of joint owners of KDE -
quite a responsibility. Dictated by the principle of congruence of
power and responsibility the membership in turn assumes the right to
allocate funds, elect representatives to related communities et
cetera. Because of that, it is necessary that the KDE e.V. membership
represents the community of KDE contributors as broadly as
possible. Every committed KDE contributor is encouraged to seek
membership. Send an email to the &lt;a href="https://mail.kde.org/mailman/listinfo/kde-community" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE community mailing
list&lt;/a> to express
your interest to become a member (&lt;a href="http://ev.kde.org/getinvolved/members.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How to become a KDE
e.V. member&lt;/a>). Only
individuals can be members, organizations are invited to become
supporting members. As a bonus, supporting members are invited to
attend the general assembly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This year&amp;rsquo;s assembly started routinely with the report of the board
and the different &lt;a href="http://ev.kde.org/workinggroups/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">working
groups&lt;/a>. Official meeting minutes
will be published later, but it is fair to say that KDE&amp;rsquo;s house is
generally in good order. The board is focused on the transition of
the KDE community to an umbrella for various Free Software efforts as
described in the &lt;a href="http://manifesto.kde.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE Manifesto&lt;/a>. As
projects join the KDE Community, the existing structure of internal
representation needs to be updated to reflect the interests of these
sub-communities. As everything in KDE this is a work in progress, the
first step look rather promising. The marketing working group is
preparing a campaign to advertise the use of the upcoming KDE
frameworks on top of Qt. The treasurer and the auditors of
the accounting reported a small surplus in the fiscal year of 2012
that will be used to fund additional KDE activities
in 2013. Spending is well aligned with KDE e.V.&amp;rsquo;s goal and tightly
supervised. A new system of accounts and cost codes will provide
better insight in the income and expenses incurred by the various
activities and events.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The mission of the User Working Group established in 2012 is the give
KDE users a representation within the community and &lt;a href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-is-open-source-democratic/">involve them more
in KDE
development&lt;/a>. This
effort still needs more pickup. Growing the role of the User Working
Group is very important, since the strength of Free Software is only
realised by users and developers forming the communities together. It
will need a charter, user representatives to KDE e.V., and routine
activities of involving KDE users in development and quality
improvement efforts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Community Working Group moderates how contributors work
together. The principle of KDE e.V. assuming a passive, supporting
role is routinely challenged whenever the community asks the Community
Working Group to resolve conflicts. The KDE Manifesto makes it very
clear that KDE is an inclusive community with a strong sense for
intrinsically motivated, voluntary contribution. Exercising authority
in such a setup is tricky - it should be reduced to a minimum, however
that minimum needs to be determined in some way. Even occasional
abuse, rudeness or bad manners set the tone of the community and can
cause substantial damage. So far KDE in general lacks instruments to
control that damage effectively. Sadly, few individual cases were not
resolved for extended periods of time, causing contributors to leave
the community. The discussion of how to empower the Community Working
Group and find a generic way to manage such situations took ginormous
time, but was definitely worth it. However, it is not over. A conflict
resolution BoF session was held on Monday, and a policy will be
proposed to the membership in the weeks after Akademy. The Community
Working Group has earned a lot of respect by me and many others with
the prudent and calm way it handles these issues, especialy
considering the amount of frustration dealing with such issues can
cause. It needs the support of all of us to define how the standards
set by the KDE Manifesto and the &lt;a href="http://www.kde.org/code-of-conduct/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Code of
Conduct&lt;/a> can be achieved.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Albert Astals Cid was elected for the vacant board seat in an
incredibly tight race (a tie in the first round of voting, and a
one vote win in the second). Competitive votes like that show that
there is choice, and that the future of KDE is defined by the
contributors. Congratulations, Albert! Many thanks to both Albert and
Marta Rybczynska for their candidacy, and to everybody who grilled the
candidates during the questions and answers session. Sebastian Kügler
stepped down after being a board member since 2006 - many thanks to
him as well for all the great work he has done. Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://mail.kde.org/mailman/listinfo/kde-community" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE
Community mailing
list&lt;/a> to get
involved in KDE governance matters. Consider joining one of the
working groups to support them in their important work. At last, the
&lt;a href="http://ev.kde.org/reports/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quarterly reports&lt;/a> help in staying up to
date with KDE e.V.s work.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Is Open Source democratic?</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-is-open-source-democratic/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2012 18:08:50 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-is-open-source-democratic/</guid><description>&lt;p>In his recent post, Glyn Moody asks an important
question -
&lt;a href="http://www.h-online.com/open/features/Can-open-source-be-democratic-1663702.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;Can Open Source be democratic?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> He
describes how Free Software emerged as a distributed, bottom-up system
of writing code. The central defining aspects of that culture are a
uniquely open process not just of programming but also of its
organization, and a close relationship between programmers and
users. Effectively, users and programmers together were both
contributors, they collaborated on the project. Glyn goes on to
explain how this community effort changed over time to become more
institutionalized, more corporate and more dull - &amp;ldquo;becoming a &amp;lsquo;Firefox
Affiliate&amp;rsquo;, hardly something that sets the pulse racing.&amp;rdquo; Ordinary
users no longer play an important part in Open Source projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-for-aristotle-the-underlying-principle-of-democracy-is-freedom-since-only-in-a-democracy-the-citizens-can-have-a-share-in-freedom">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Aristotle" srcset="
/media/img/post/aristotle-altemps_hue90612a493a95dbd18bbb2231dca5ed8_2244558_b6ea70e7a2f1482223e96218d8fd5a3c.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/aristotle-altemps_hue90612a493a95dbd18bbb2231dca5ed8_2244558_5eb5225b08c9fe87efc059f0e7e5aa3b.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/aristotle-altemps_hue90612a493a95dbd18bbb2231dca5ed8_2244558_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/aristotle-altemps_hue90612a493a95dbd18bbb2231dca5ed8_2244558_b6ea70e7a2f1482223e96218d8fd5a3c.webp"
width="60%"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
For Aristotle the underlying principle of democracy is freedom, since only in a democracy the citizens can have a share in freedom.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Underlying is the assumption that Open Source is democratic, and this
assumption needs to be questioned. Open Source communities have been
coined to be self-directed, meritocratic,  &amp;hellip;, but it is rarely
emphasized that they are democratic. Since individuals are investing
effort in their favorite projects to contribute to something greater,
and democracy is commonly considered to be a greater good as well, it
is intriguing to make the jump to thinking of Open Source communities
as being democratic. But are they? What is the meaning of democracy in
the context of Open Source? What does a democratic community look
like?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some may say that such political concepts cannot easily be transferred
to how Open Source communities should function. While it may not be
easy, it is still worthwhile - democracies have dealt with similar
problems of inclusion and the distribution of power and
responsibility. Just like democratic states, communities are volunteer
organizations that congregate to build the public goods they desire in
the commons. Just like citizens, members of communities have a choice
of voice or exit that they make based on the expected influence they
have as citizens. There are enough similarities to justify learning by
example.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="on-being-a-contributor">On being a contributor&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Democracy means &amp;ldquo;rule of the people&amp;rdquo;, and postulates, amongst other
things, for each individual to be equal before the law and to have a
vote in the political process and election of the government. This
immediately boils down to the central Yin-Yang question of who is a
citizen and who is not. Are users considered integral parts (citizens)
of the Open Source communities, or outsiders who provide feedback? And
should they be the equals of developers?  While today we seem to think
that equality comes standard, it is in fact a dynamic concept, its
meaning changes with culture. Think about the Voting Rights Act of
1965 that finally abolished voter&amp;rsquo;s discrimination by race in the US,
or the fact that women will gain the right to vote in Saudi Arabia in
the year 2015. This is what Glyn observes - users changed from being
integral elements of the community to playing an only marginal role,
akin to not having a vote.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Eligibility and acceptance are what discerns citizens from barbarians
and slaves. Eligibility answers the question of which individuals can
potentially become citizens. Acceptance is the requirements an
eligible individual has to fulfill to gain citizenship. For example, a
foreigner living in a country may be eligible for citizenship, but to
be accepted needs to pay taxes for a number of years. When the same
questions are applied to Open Source communities, they translate to
&amp;ldquo;Who is a contributor and could thus become a citizen of our
community? How does somebody join the project?&amp;rdquo; and second, &amp;ldquo;What
does a newcomer have to do to be considered a contributor, a part of
the community?&amp;rdquo; (does that sound like &amp;ldquo;How do I become a committer&amp;rdquo;? -
exactly). In Open Source communities usually all individuals are
eligible to join, but to be accepted and integrated, they need to
&lt;em>contribute to the code&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So for users to become integral parts of Open Source communities
again, users that engage with an Open Source project need to be equal
contributors amongst peers, to be eligible. This is far from standard,
and not the mind-set of most contributors I know. Most communities I
work with value direct contributions to the project source code higher
than feedback from users. They (unconsciously?) consider users
outsiders and refer them to talk to the issue tracker, a proven way to
make sure they never come back again with more feedback. So firstly,
users need to be considered eligible to become community members, and
second their efforts (feedback, for example) need to qualify them for
acceptance as ordinary contributors.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="on-open-governance">On Open Governance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>But not all communities are created equal. When evaluating how
democratic a community is, we need to look at their reason to
exist. Not all Open Source projects are created by developers and
users together, and the distribution of power and responsibility
usually follows this outset goal or doctrine. If a project that is
founded by developers and users  grows organically into an openly
governed community (like KDE), it is likened to a democracy. A project
that is founded by a company (think Mozilla or Qt) and maybe allows
external contributors in along as they accept the decrees^wCLA of the
king^wowner company aches more towards an aristocracy. Not all
contributors are equals, and the ruling government cannot be replaced.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There has been a long debate over what the most central trait of a
democracy is. Opinions differ, but there is one question - can the
citizens, on a regular basis, re-elect or replace the ruling
government in a structured process, without the need for a revolution?
With this argument in mind, it becomes apparent that not all Open
Source communities are democratic. KDE is to an extend, with a weak
government and regular elections where every active member has exactly
one vote. Think about electing a new government for Android, and the
difference becomes apparent. Of the Open Source projects Glyn
mentioned in his post, few can be considered democratic by this
standard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Back to the question on how to reduce the distance between users and
developers and how to build communities that thrive on
collaboration. Users, like any contributor, will consider the effect
their investment of time into the project will have. If the utility
they gain from contributing outweighs the cost of the effort to
contribute, they will join the community and help with the
project. The utility is directly related to the openness of the
community governance; it will be less if the contributor&amp;rsquo;s influence
is only on mundane details, and greater if she has the chance to
become the next president of KDE e.V. This emphasizes the importance
of Open Governance for the longevity and community spirit of Open
Source projects. Only with both the Open Source way and Open
Governance, the user experiences the freedom to create that convinces
her to join the project. Democracy in communities is Open Source
combined with Open Governance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>From the status of being a contributor - a citizen - follows
the
&lt;a href="https://endocode.com/blog/2012/03/16/managing-trust-in-mixed-commercial-and-volunteer-open-source-communities/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">right and duty&lt;/a> to
take part in the community&amp;rsquo;s affairs. Open Source can be democratic if
it treats all the community members equally. Three requirements for
considering an Open Source community democratic have been developed in
the discussion above:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>To be democratic requires not to discriminate amongst contributors
(users and developers). Users are contributors. They need to be
encouraged to join the community, to give feedback and to otherwise
help improve the project.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Demmocracy in communities means Open Source combined with Open
Governance. The availability of the source code under a Free
Software license is not sufficient for an Open Source community to
be democratic. Without equality, without the contributors
controlling the project as equals, it may be Open Source, but it is
not democratic.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Governance is open if the contributors are equals and the community
elects its own representation. Defining Open Governance as the
situation where the contributors are in control of their project on
all levels, democracy in an Open Source project can only be achieved
when all contributors have equal say on all matters of the project.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Whether or not contributors fully are equals amongst peers can only be
decided by actions, not by words. The ethical question whether or not
democracy is desirable for an Open Source project has been avoided in
this article. In my personal opinion, Glyn is absolutely right: For
Open Source to continue being successful, direct and indirect
contributors need to get back to working together. With the widening
appeal of Open Source software, naturally developers will become more
experienced and professional, and the average user will turn to be
less technical and computer savvy. This trend will likely continue
with the growing user base of Open Source. And because it is
inevitable, Open Source projects should instead prepare to liaise more
with users and generally get good at integrating users and coders in
the community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p style="text-align: center; font-size: 80%;">&lt;a
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en_US"
rel="license">&lt;img style="border-width: 0;"
src="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/80x15.png" alt="Creative
Commons License" />&lt;/a> This work is licensed under a &lt;a
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en_US"
rel="license">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
License&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>It's the Free Software, stupid!</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-its-the-free-software-stupid/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2012 18:08:50 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-its-the-free-software-stupid/</guid><description>&lt;p>Heated discussions are going on in the KDE community in the aftermath
of the announcement of Nokia&amp;rsquo;s platform strategy change. Rationality
often goes out of the window when people feel such a change goes
against their personal values or beliefs. In the past days, I worked
on an analysis of the impact of the changes on KDAB, Qt and the Free
Software communities we work with, especially KDE. KDAB is rooted
deeply in the KDE community, and many of our developers work with Qt
and KDE for years now. We are sharing the same worries and hopes, so
the results may be interesting for others as well. This post is about
Qt, KDE, Free Software, politics, devices, markets, strategies - it
does not get much better than that. Read on.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="be-thankful-for-what-you-got">Be thankful for what you got&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We are told to judge by actions, not by words, so let us have a look
at the development of Qt since Nokia bought Trolltech, and how the KDE
community benefitted from it. It is important to stress this up front
because it is easy to forget that since then, Nokia has been a very
important benefactor. KDE is based on Qt and always relied heavily
it&amp;rsquo;s technical advances. Trolltech convinced many developers to use Qt
because of it&amp;rsquo;s superior quality and ease of use and the friendly and
inspiring developer community. But it was a small company, and could
not have afforded to forgo the license revenue made from selling
commercial Qt licenses. This revenue was the central pillar of
Trolltech&amp;rsquo;s business model. Trolltech was also in the uneasy situation
that it influenced the software industry way more than it&amp;rsquo;s small size
warranted, and attracted the attention of much larger
competitors. With the takeover, the revenue Trolltech generated was to
a large extend irrelevant to Nokia. The development framework is a
strategic asset, and selling Qt licenses is not in line with Nokia&amp;rsquo;s
core competencies. It also made perfect business sense to invest even
more resources that could never have been afforded from the license
revenue, to be able to rely on Qt as the future UI platform. This
investment resulted in huge performance improvements, new technologies
like QML, a continuous stable development process with many releases,
Qt Creator, and many other goodies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But the biggest gift Nokia ever presented us with was to relicense Qt
under the LGPL. It finally overcame the acceptance issue with Qt in
the wider Free Software space, and helped grow the Qt user base
massively. While other important safeguards like the Free Qt
Foundation were already in place, using Qt under the LGPL license is
so much less of a hurdle to take then to enforce the rights granted
through the Free Qt Foundation. Those rights can also only be executed
once, and only as an action of last resort. Without Qt under LGPL,
MeeGo would not have been accepted by the software industry. This, the
public hosting of the Qt git repo and the massive development manpower
Nokia invested in Qt benefit KDE immensely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The best part is that none of these presents can be un-given or taken
away. Qt is there to stay under the current Free Software licenses,
and the quality it gained in the recent years will also remain at
KDE&amp;rsquo;s service. There are new developments in KDE like QML and QtQuick
that KDE still has to fully make use of. Today&amp;rsquo;s Qt is a superb
platform to base the development of KDE on in the coming
years. Thanks, Nokia.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="qt">Qt&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It is an open question how these past achievements translate into the
future when it comes to Qt&amp;rsquo;s own development. From talking to business
partners and contacts at Nokia, it is pretty clear that no new
direction has been set for the Qt unit at Nokia. The announcement that
there will be no layoffs or budget cuts is comforting, but it needs to
be taken with a grain of salt. It may have all kinds of reasons, for
example personnel retention, local labor laws, maintaining an
undamaged business unit that can be sold - or the simple lack of an
updated strategy. So all these statements have to be mentally extended
with an &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;until further notice&amp;rdquo;. By definition, strategy changes do
not occur on a regular basis. Even if the Microsoft partnership is
unsuccessful (in sales figures, for example), it will take 3 to 5
years for that to be realized and the strategy to be re-evaluated. In
that time frame, there will most certainly be changes to the Qt unit
if it remains within Nokia.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="checking-the-facts-about-nokia-platforms-shipping-qt">Checking the facts about Nokia platforms shipping Qt&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Nokia plans to ship another 150 million Symbian devices with Qt
installed. The ability to do so depends heavily on the appeal of these
phones to users willing to pay more than the magical 100 Euro barrier
price. A vivid app market is necessary to reach this goal, since apps
are a major sales driver in today&amp;rsquo;s smartphones. Will companies keep
investing in the fledgling Symbian plus Qt app space? Investors shy
away from shrinking markets. Every corporate strategist tasked with
developing a product-market-matrix will put anything Symbian related
into the &amp;ldquo;de-invest&amp;rdquo; bracket. Why does the Symbian market shrink? Have
a look at the diagram that visualizes the spectrum of Nokia phones
(while creating the image I discovered how close the Qt and the
Windows Phone 7 shades of green are - a coincidence? I guess we will
never know).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-the-nokia-qt-dilemma">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="The Nokia Qt Dilemma" srcset="
/media/img/post/2012-nokia-qt-dilemma_hu0d5d37beef49274c4e61e30a7df5301e_22889_a3a12e7c6d10a6aff2715f8178d27842.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2012-nokia-qt-dilemma_hu0d5d37beef49274c4e61e30a7df5301e_22889_146dd0e61a7e03ea14367ea30581d1a7.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2012-nokia-qt-dilemma_hu0d5d37beef49274c4e61e30a7df5301e_22889_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2012-nokia-qt-dilemma_hu0d5d37beef49274c4e61e30a7df5301e_22889_a3a12e7c6d10a6aff2715f8178d27842.webp"
width="60%"
height="156"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
The Nokia Qt Dilemma
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The lower end S30/S40 devices are becoming more attractive because
features are added to them that so far required a smart
phone. Internet access becomes more and more pervasive, and apps are
being developed for these devices now. Having a Facebook app, for
example, will be a convincing argument for those buyers who never
really wanted a clunky smartphone. Also, these not-so-dumb phones will
continue to be developed and shipped under the new strategy, resulting
in better customer acceptance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Through constantly improving hardware, the smartphones are being sold
at steadily decreasing prices. The cheapest Android phones are now at
below 100 Euro. This puts additional pressure on the sales revenue
generated by the current high-end Symbian phones. Customer acceptance
plays an important role in this segment as well. Read the latest
tweets, and half of them are in the line of &amp;ldquo;I finally got rid of my
Nokia and got an Android phone now&amp;rdquo;. Customers will shy away from a
line of phones that is already announced to be replaced. It is like
beating the proverbial dead horse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So the Symbian market segment will shrink, and with that the
importance (and clout) of Qt within Nokia. Customers do not care about
mobile OSes to a large extend. As soon as an average S40 phone will
ship apps and have internet access, the middle bracket in the above
diagram will fade away. Nokia is trying to define a &amp;ldquo;mid range phone&amp;rdquo;
segment between the feature phones (S30/S40) and the smartphone (WP7)
ranges. This segment is not established in the phone market, and it is
questionable whether there will be a niche for it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Because of that, app developers will hesitate to invest in the
platform, and the Qt mobile ecosystem will be under a lot of
pressure. In all the Nokia devices, Qt will not gain the widest
coverage of all development platforms. Very likely it will be S30/S40,
by device count, and WP7, by sales volume. Remember this is about Qt
within Nokia. It only influences KDE indirectly, by defining Qt&amp;rsquo;s role
in the platform strategy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="qt-on-other-mobile-platforms">Qt on other Mobile Platforms&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>With apps currently being developed in Java for the S30/S40 based
phones, Nokia uses 3 different development platforms for it&amp;rsquo;s phone
lineup, Java, Symbian with Qt, and WP7.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a hopelessly romantic rumor that Qt support might come for
the S30/S40 platform. A reality check is needed here. The low-end
devices are shipping with S30/S40 because it is available today, not
because it is a great modern future-proof platform. The apps for these
phones are being developed now, or within the next twelve months. Even
if a full-scale Qt port is started today, it won&amp;rsquo;t be available
short-term. No doubt the Qt community will be able to pull off that
stunt. But finishing the port is one thing, getting it through quality
acceptance and to the point where it is shipped in devices is
another. App developers would only target those devices when they
gained a sufficient market share, and by that time, an Android phone
sells for 50 Euro. Because of that, I do not think there will be an
official strategy to make Qt available on S30/S40. And since Qt is
also not coming to to WP7, Qt&amp;rsquo;s cross platform claim is moot within
Nokia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the Qt ports to Androids, Blackberries, Badas and Kindles become a
viable reality, other vendors will sell more devices supporting Qt
than Nokia. And that is a development going on now, while Nokia will
need between one and two years to release the first WP7 phone. These
forces will heavily impede Nokia&amp;rsquo;s ability to differentiate based on
the features of Qt, and result in less motivation to base a future
strategy on Qt as a disruptive technology. The disruption will happen
while Nokia is developing it&amp;rsquo;s first WP7 phone.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="open-governance-of-qt">Open Governance of Qt&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Regarding Open Governance, it is another open question if this strategy is
viable for Qt in the absence of a major investor (of time and money)
that drives the development. There is a good chance that it ends up
like XFree.org and produces little more than bike shedding for a long
time. Free Software projects under Open Governance, like the Linux
kernel, or X.org, or - not quite the same, but very similar - the C++
standard, tend to innovate slowly. Because of that, I am not convinced
that an impressive Qt 5 can be developed by the community under Open
Governance in a reasonable time frame. Do not get this wrong: The idea
is great, the problem is that it might not work out as we all hope
for. Three major scenarios come to mind when thinking about the future
of Qt&amp;rsquo;s governance:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Nokia considers Qt a strategic asset, and continues to heavily
invest in it. In this case, Open Governance has a chance to
succeed, but might not be in Nokia&amp;rsquo;s own interest, since it will be
losing control over it&amp;rsquo;s own important technology.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Qt is switched into maintenance mode, because it is not seen as
important for the future. In this case, Open Governance will have a
hard time to be implemented in the first place, and partners will
hesitate to take responsibility for individual modules.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nokia plans to sell the Qt unit as an asset. In this case, the
potential buyer will want enforceable control over it&amp;rsquo;s
investment. For that plan, Open Governance devalues Qt as a
sellable product. The biggest challenge for the transition to Open
Governance is to make sure the companies invested in Qt support it
fully, and want to see it happen.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Maybe I missed a scenario that will make it work? Please post your
feedback.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The biggest challenge for Qt itself will be the potential talent
drain. Qt attracted excellent developers from all over the world
because it was innovative and elite. Those are people that won&amp;rsquo;t be
comfortable with being parked on the back burner, and might not feel
at home with Nokia anymore. At the same time, they do not exactly have
problems finding another job. It will be hard for Nokia to convince
employees not to leave, and also to hire new talent of the same
quality. This is a long-term threat to the quality of Qt, and it&amp;rsquo;s
ability to innovate.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="countering-the-threat-of-free-software-in-the-mobile-market">Countering the &amp;ldquo;threat&amp;rdquo; of Free Software in the mobile market&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Android based devices and Nokia smartphones together make up 64% of
the global smartphone market at the time of this writing, according to
Wikipedia (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smartphone%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smartphone)&lt;/a>. If Nokia would
have successfully transitioned to a MeeGo based smartphone line with
Qt GUIs, the majority of the mobile devices market would use Free
Software based development tools, on open and inviting ecosystems for
developers, a competitive app market with low entry barriers, all in
all promising innovation and affordable devices. Nokia was looking for
a solution for it&amp;rsquo;s future platform problem, and it was determined to
base it on Free Software. The stock market loved the idea. Google
agreed, too, and made Android.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the same time, market demand for Windows based phones is at an
overall low. There is simply no need for another closed proprietary
phone OS, considering the alternatives. The tendency of it becoming an
accepted standard that phone software platforms should be based on
Free Software threatens Microsofts investment in WP7, and it&amp;rsquo;s general
position as a closed operating system vendor. WP7 was a solution
looking for a problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is probably a large overlap of institutional investors in Nokia
and Microsoft, given that they are both market leaders and publicly
traded companies. Both companies see their markets under siege, and
are not doing very well, so it might have sounded like a good idea at
the time to combine the hardware vendor looking for a phone OS with
the phone OS vendor looking for hardware. The partnership is
unbalanced though, because if it fails, Microsoft will still be the
market leader in PC OS installations, and Nokia will have lost
relevance in the global smart phone market. The stock market did not
love that idea so much.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But it is seriously hard to believe that simply pushing WP7 to the
market was Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s only motivation. Also, there are other vendors
that started offering WP7 phones. So why Nokia? There must be another
compelling reason for Microsoft to first send a top-ranking emissary
to Nokia, and then form a partnership that by all the usual criteria
looks like a takeover. This reason that was important enough for
Microsoft to invest billions into Nokia was to battle Free Software in
it&amp;rsquo;s emerging mobile market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The strategic goal of ensuring that future phone OSes are based on
proprietary and in particular not on Free Software was very likely the
major motivator for Microsoft to pursue this unequal partnership. The
recent ban of Free Software from the Microsoft app store indicates a
similar motivation. Nokia&amp;rsquo;s Free Software based platform strategy is
dead, and it will not come back. This means Microsoft achieved one
strategic goal immediately by establishing the partnership and
aborting Nokia&amp;rsquo;s Free Software based efforts. If this move was about
WP7 introduction into the market, why rely on the stumbling giant
Nokia, and not on one of the hungry Asian tigers, like HTC, who are
already offering WP7 phones? Because those did not have a Free
Software based strategy. Maemo or MeeGo together with Android are a
thought unbearable to Microsoft.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>About Qt - Qt was a compelling toolkit that developers loved to work
with before Nokia bought it. That is the real reason for it&amp;rsquo;s
success. Developers tell their managers that they want to use Qt
rather than something else. That quality of Qt has gotten even
better. This is why I think Qt will continue to be strong and - after
the shakeout happening now - to grow in both the Free Software and the
commercial development spaces. Qt reputation with decision makers has
been damaged, though. They regarded it not only as stable from a
software point of view, but also as being trustworthy from a
development process and maintenance point of view. This image has been
severely tarnished. So for now, the Qt market will shrink because
mobile users will leave, and it will recover and grow at a slower rate
afterwards due to the reduced willingness of developers and decision
makers to invest in it. The change of pace might be a good thing for
Qt itself after the recent coding marathons it went through. The
trolls will work hard on keeping Qt the best and one and only true
cross-platform UI toolkit on the planet. I wish them all the best for
the turbulent time to come. Hug a troll, everybody!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>About KDE - KDE as a technology will not be affected much right
now. Qt is Free Software and does not change over night. There are
enough great new features that KDE still has to digest. Even the
longer term outlook of the strategy for Qt only has an indirect effect
on KDE. Not many developers joined KDE because of the prospect of Qt
on mobile phones, so even the community will remain stable. The
development focus of Qt becomes broader again, away from concentrating
on features for the mobile space. Whether Nokia will continue to
support KDE at the same scale as in the last years is mostly a PR
decision, so it is also not related to the more technical aspects
described above. It will depend on the friendly relationship that has
been developed so far, and how it continues. Nonetheless, the next KDE
version will be shipped on time. KDE is in good shape.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>About Free Software - Nokia&amp;rsquo;s strategy change is a very sad
development in this regard, because it is not just about Qt. Microsoft
is trying to prevent Free Software from becoming mainstream in the
mobile space. Beside the feeling that it is already too late for that,
the process raises the question if such activity against the GNU
competition should be concerning the regulators. Antitrust and other
market law protects businesses from unfair competition, but
unfortunately it does not protect Free Software communities or
projects from being bullied. Indirectly preventing a competitor from
entering the market, for example, can be a reason for the antitrust
agencies to not approve such a partnership, but only if large
businesses are involved that are able to prevent the usual market
forces from working. This is a political issue, and needs to be
brought forward to policy makers. Our interests, those of Free
Software as a force to create better working and more competitive
markets, are not sufficiently represented there. That is why I will
join the FSFE.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks for reading.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>