<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Microsoft | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/microsoft/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/microsoft/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Microsoft</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 15:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Microsoft</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/microsoft/</link></image><item><title>Microsoft Joins the Open Invention Network Community</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2018-microsoft-joins-oin/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2018-microsoft-joins-oin/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today, &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Microsoft&lt;/a>
and
&lt;a href="https://www.openinventionnetwork.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Invention Network (OIN)&lt;/a>
announced that Microsoft has become a member of the OIN community. OIN
is the largest patent non-aggression community in history with over
2.600 community member companies. It&amp;rsquo;s mission is to protect core Open
Source technologies from patent litigation. It shapes the norms of
collaboration as Open Source becomes more industrial and the edge
between free and proprietary software becomes increasingly
important. Many key innovators license their patent portfolio through
OIN, including Google, IBM, NEC, Philip, Red Hat, Sony, SUSE and
Toyota. Until now however, one party was missing from the community
that became an increasingly important contributor to Open Source
technologies, and that was Microsoft. This gap closes today. I believe
this is a historic moment that will encourage innovation and
dramatically reduces risks for the wider Open Source community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am a Free Software contributor for more than twenty
years. Contributing for me was always about working towards the
creation of a large body of Free and Open Source Software that
benefits everybody. It was never about working &lt;em>against&lt;/em> something or
some entity. Later, I
started
&lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/mirkoboehm/cebit-opensourceforumpresentation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presenting about Free Software arguing that &amp;ldquo;companies are community&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>,
a notion that at the time caused concern with many long-term Free
Software contributors. For me, this emphasizes that the Open Source
way is about working towards open collaboration with all interested
contributors.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Microsoft loves Linux" srcset="
/media/img/post/ms_loves_linux_hu858ac22adcb60b943640e1c9219703f6_10351_ea93f1ebb78ff07397f2c83d0fcf311f.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/ms_loves_linux_hu858ac22adcb60b943640e1c9219703f6_10351_37d4e6ee313d7ef76771d2ce61e3a30e.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/ms_loves_linux_hu858ac22adcb60b943640e1c9219703f6_10351_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/ms_loves_linux_hu858ac22adcb60b943640e1c9219703f6_10351_ea93f1ebb78ff07397f2c83d0fcf311f.webp"
width="653"
height="367"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>When Free Software emerged, it was a strong competitor for all
incumbent proprietary software vendors, and Microsoft was one of the
largest of them. Some initial conflict was inevitable. However,
attitudes change and everybody learns. Eventually, Microsoft rather
impressively reinvented itself as an important Open Source
contributor. The announcement today is a culmination of the process
that completes for patent licensing what began with code releases and
major contributions to various
projects. Today,
&lt;a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/linux-now-dominates-azure/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Linux based workloads on Azure are quite common&lt;/a>. For
Microsoft, joining OIN resolves an inherent conflict that existed as a
leftover from the transition to being a major Free Software
contributor: If technologies are developed collaboratively, the
contributors should exercise joint stewardship over the result that is
released under an Open Source license. Extracting license revenue from
such collaboratively developed Open Source technology creates a rift
and undermines collaboration. By &amp;ldquo;making peace with the free world&amp;rdquo;
and joining OIN,
Microsoft
&lt;a href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/microsoft-may-relinquishing-billions-android-patent-royalties-141047213.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may pre-empt it&amp;rsquo;s own patent licensing revenue for Android and other technologies&lt;/a> covered
by the OIN Linux System definition, but it gains significant
reputation and acceptance in the wider Open Source community. Since
this is where software innovation is happening, the long-term benefits
of this strategy should outweigh the cost by far.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Open Invention Network" srcset="
/media/img/post/OIN_logo_300dpi_hub65928be94d50260b17e2296b1257b3e_51500_48cfd80b25a83cac0be03fb23ad09af2.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/OIN_logo_300dpi_hub65928be94d50260b17e2296b1257b3e_51500_5598af508c627ee70e216ed42dfdaeec.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/OIN_logo_300dpi_hub65928be94d50260b17e2296b1257b3e_51500_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/OIN_logo_300dpi_hub65928be94d50260b17e2296b1257b3e_51500_48cfd80b25a83cac0be03fb23ad09af2.webp"
width="760"
height="74"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>For Open Invention Network, today&amp;rsquo;s news are a major step
forward. Membership in the OIN community is free of charge. All
participants cross-license their patent portfolio within the
field-of-use definition of core Open Source technologies. It is not
necessary to hold a patent portfolio to join OIN. This means everybody
in the network immediately benefits from the
new
&lt;a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/blog/microsoft-joins-open-invention-network-to-help-protect-linux-and-open-source/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cross-licensing commitment of over 60.000 patents&lt;/a> made
by Microsoft. A network like OIN becomes more and more valuable the
more patents are cross-licensed and the more software technologies are
covered by that (a network effect :-). With Microsoft on board, it
should be even more obvious
that
&lt;a href="https://www.openinventionnetwork.com/joining-oin/join-now/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">joining OIN&lt;/a> is
the best and also the easiest way to enter the patent “no-fly zone”
over Linux. This benefits Open Source innovation and the wider Open
Source community, which in turn contributes Free Software to the
common good. Everybody wins.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>