<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>threadweaver | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/threadweaver/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/threadweaver/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>threadweaver</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 18:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>threadweaver</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/threadweaver/</link></image><item><title>HelW olorld! - Concurrent programming using the ThreadWeaver framework</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2014-08-11-helw-olorld/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2014-08-11-helw-olorld/</guid><description>&lt;p>Concurrent programming means creating applications that perform
multiple operations at the same time. A common problem is that the
user sees the application pause. A typical requirement is that an
operation which may take an arbitrary amount of time because it is,
for example, performing disk I/O, is scheduled for execution but
immediately taken of the main thread of the application (the one that
starts &lt;code>main()&lt;/code>). To illustrate how this problem would be solved and to
jump right into using ThreadWeaver, let&amp;rsquo;s simulate this problem by
printing &lt;em>Hello World!&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> as the asynchronous payload:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-c++" data-lang="c++">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#include&lt;/span> &lt;span class="cpf">&amp;lt;QtCore&amp;gt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="cp">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#include&lt;/span> &lt;span class="cpf">&amp;lt;ThreadWeaver/ThreadWeaver&amp;gt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="cp">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nf">main&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">argc&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">char&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">**&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">argv&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">QCoreApplication&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">app&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">argc&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">argv&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">using&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">namespace&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">ThreadWeaver&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">stream&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">()&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">make_job&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">[]()&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">qDebug&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">()&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Hello World!&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>This short but complete program written in C++11 outputs the common
greeting to the command line.&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> It does so, however, from a worker
thread managed by the global ThreadWeaver queue. The header file
&lt;code>ThreadWeaver/ThreadWeaver&lt;/code> included in line 2 contains the essential
declarations needed to use the most common ThreadWeaver
operations. The components used in this examples are the global queue,
a job and a queueing mechanism. The global queue is a singleton
instance of the ThreadWeaver thread pool that is instantiated when it
it first accessed after the application starts. A job represents
&amp;ldquo;something&amp;rdquo; that should be executed asynchroneously. In this case, the
thing to execute is a C++ lambda function that prints the welcome
message. The queueing mechanism used here is a queue stream, an API
inspired by the &lt;em>iostream&lt;/em> family of classes. ThreadWeaver builds on
top of Qt, and similar to most Qt applications requires a
QCoreApplication (or one of its descendants) to exist throughout the
lifetime of the application. Up to line 7, the program looks like any
other Qt application.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To have the job lambda function called by one of the worker threads, a
job is created that wraps it using the &lt;code>make_job()&lt;/code>. It is then handed
to the queue stream. The queue stream will submit the jobs for
execution when the queuing command is completed, that is at the
closing semicolon. Once the job is queued, one of the worker threads
will automatically pick it up from the queue and execute
it. &lt;code>ThreadWeaver::Job&lt;/code> is the unit of execution handled by
ThreadWeaver queues. Jobs are simple runnable types that perform one
task, defined in their &lt;code>run()&lt;/code> method. Some jobs wrap a
lambda function as in this example or decorate other jobs. However
implementing custom, reusable job classes is only a matter of writing
a class that inherits &lt;code>ThreadWeaver::Job&lt;/code> and re-implementing
it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code>run&lt;/code> method. The job that was created by &lt;code>make_job()&lt;/code>
in this example wraps the specified lambda function, and executes it
when it is itself executed by a worker thread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The program does not specify where the job should be executed, and not
even when exactly. In a scenario where there would be many jobs
waiting in the queue, execution of the new job would not be
immediate. Which worker thread will be assigned the job is also
undefined. The programmer gives up a bit of control over the details
of execution, and in turns benefits from the automatic distribution of
jobs amongst the available processors by the worker threads in the
queue. Every program that links the ThreadWeaver library has access to
a global queue for the execution of jobs. If no queue is specified
when enqueueing a job, the global one will be used by default. Workers
threads are allocated when needed by the queue. If the global pool is
never accessed by an application, it will never be instantiated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An application performing tasks in background threads should never
exit while any of these operations is still in progress. In the case
of ThreadWeaver, this means all jobs in the queue need to be either
completed or dequeued and all worker threads idle before the
application may exit. The global pool is in fact a QObject child of
the &lt;code>QCoreApplication&lt;/code> object instantiated in line 7. It will be
deleted by the destructor of QCoreApplication. When it is destroyed,
it will wait until all queued up jobs have completed. The program will
thus wait in line 8 until the job has finished printing &amp;ldquo;Hello World!&amp;rdquo;
and will then exit. The job was enqueued as a shared pointer, so
memory management is taken care of. While this example was very much
simplified, the described functionality already has many practical
applications. For example, the many operations real-life applications
need to perform at startup, like loading translations, icon resources
et cetera, can be removed from the criticial path this way. In this
case the operations usually need to be performed in a certain order
and then handed over to the main thread. Solutions for that are built
into ThreadWeaver as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Since there have been questions - the title of the post refers to the problem of writing output from multiple threads without synchronization, which breaks the guarantees on order of execution. A boon for every concurrent program.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>The examples are part of the ThreadWeaver source code and can be found in the &lt;a href="https://api.kde.org/frameworks/threadweaver/html/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE API DOCS&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>KDE Frameworks 5 Tech Preview released, with updated ThreadWeaver</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2014-01-07-kde-frameworks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2014-01-07-kde-frameworks/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today, the KDE Community &lt;a href="http://dot.kde.org/2014/01/07/frameworks-5-tech-preview" target="_blank" rel="noopener">released a tech preview of the upcoming KDE
5
Frameworks&lt;/a>,
the new, modularised incarnation of what was previously distributed
simply as the KDE libraries. The new frameworks are drop-in extensions
to Qt applications, with minimal and well-documented dependencies for
easier deployment. The tech preview contains two frameworks that are
marked as mature, namely KArchive and ThreadWeaver. The updated
ThreadWeaver was my major piece of library coding work in 2013, and
was finished just in time for the release. Even though it is a tech
preview, it is stable, and no major (or even significant but minor)
changes in the current API are expected until the final
release. Programmers are already encouraged to use it, and provide
feedback and bug reports.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Recycled Paper Weaving" srcset="
/media/img/post/2014-01-07-weaving_huc8ec5acf46b1ae12e7aa9cfc79db2e80_262694_55ef0e7e90032ace5ae5d1f43bbf7101.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2014-01-07-weaving_huc8ec5acf46b1ae12e7aa9cfc79db2e80_262694_5ed878cde768578fe581f66754e24041.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2014-01-07-weaving_huc8ec5acf46b1ae12e7aa9cfc79db2e80_262694_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2014-01-07-weaving_huc8ec5acf46b1ae12e7aa9cfc79db2e80_262694_55ef0e7e90032ace5ae5d1f43bbf7101.webp"
width="60%"
height="720"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>ThreadWeaver is a concurrent execution scheduler written in
C++. Available for all target platforms of the Qt framework, including
desktop, mobile and embedded environments, ThreadWeaver delivers
concurrent execution of tasks, load balancing with regard to
user-defined criteria, multiple independent queues, processing graph
modelling, aggregate jobs and other comprehensive features. As all
other KDE frameworks, ThreadWeaver is Free Software. Its only
dependency is Qt, which makes it a tier 1 framework in KDE&amp;rsquo;s lingo.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A number of the &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/mirkoboehm/thread-weaver-in-kde-frameworks-5%22" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new features of
ThreadWeaver&lt;/a>
were announced at Akademy 2013. Jobs, the unit of concurrent execution
in ThreadWeaver, are now managed by the queue using shared pointers,
meaning that auto-delete behaviour is implicit and controlled by the
user. Helper templates are available to queue stack or member
variables, so allocation of jobs can be static or dynamic. Functors or
lambda functions can be used to construct jobs. Job aggregates like
collections and sequences now execute their own run() method before
queueing their elements, so that aggregates can generate their own
elements. Success and queueing state of jobs are now integrated into a
single status. Jobs can signal the result of execution by setting a
status, but also using exceptions, simplifying error reporting in more
complex job classes. Jobs can be decorated, and no more inherit
QObject by default. Decorators can be used to add signals, change
priorities or modify just about any behaviour of jobs independently of
the actual job class used. The construction of the global queue can
now be customised using a queue factory. The QueueStream API greatly
simplifies queueing jobs with a familiar iostream-like C++ syntax.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>ThreadWeaver follows the Unix idiom of doing one thing, and doing it
right. Similar to how small Unix programs can be combined to create an
practically infinite space of computing solutions, ThreadWeaver offers
itself to programmers as an add-on module with minimal
dependencies. Including it extends an application with concurrent
scheduling capability. But the same Unix idiom is also applied in a
second sense. Within ThreadWeaver, a few basic concepts – jobs and
their aggregates, queues and policies – are implemented that again
provide simple building blocks that can be combined creatively,
offering a vast space of potential solutions within the scope of the
application.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The history of ThreadWeaver goes back to KDE 3. The idea of
implementing a thread pool based execution scheduler that manages
dependencies between jobs was implemented as a proof of concept using
Qt 3. However it turned out to be difficult to implement and use
because of the lack of thread-safe reference counting of the
implicitly shared classes at the time. These fundamental problems have
been solved with the release of Qt 4. Additionally, the introduction
of cross-thread signal-slot connections further simplified the
communication between jobs and the application&amp;rsquo;s user interface. The
first production ready version of ThreadWeaver was released as part of
KDELibs with KDE 4.0. For KDE Frameworks 5, it was almost completely
re-written to simplify memory management of jobs, make use of new Qt 5
features like atomic variables, and in part to reflect new language
constructs in C++11 like lambda functions. ThreadWeaver comes with an
extensive set of unit tests that all pass in the tech preview (hear,
hear).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the following weeks and months, the framework will be polished and
debugged based on user feedback. Also, a series of posts here on this
blog will introduce individual ThreadWeaver concepts and features in
depth, mostly based on example programs, including contrasting it to
thread handling in Qt using QThread or Qt Concurrent. ThreadWeaver is
very close to production quality, having been tested continuously in
the last couple of months. There may still be smaller, source
compatible changes to the framework. We ask interested programmers out
there to provide feedback and bug reports to make ThreadWeaver what it
should be &amp;ndash; a worry-free, easy to use and powerful add-on to Qt that
programmers enjoy using. Have fun!&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/originalbliss/2897019812" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Image&lt;/a> by Shannan Sinclair, thanks&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>