<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>OFE | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/ofe/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/ofe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>OFE</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 12:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>OFE</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/ofe/</link></image><item><title>The impact of open source software and hardware on technological independence, competitiveness and innovation in the EU economy</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/eu-impact-of-open-source/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/eu-impact-of-open-source/</guid><description/></item><item><title>OpenForum Academy Workshop - Exploring Modern Dimensions of Openness</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2019-09-ofa-workshop/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2019 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2019-09-ofa-workshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>The &lt;a href="http://www.openforumeurope.org/about-ofe/openforum-academy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OpenForum
Academy&lt;/a>
held its second 2019 workshop in Brussels this week. OpenForum Academy
is a European-based independent think tank which explains the merits
of openness in computing to policy makers, industry and communities across
Europe. This workshop series aims at being a forum for practitioners,
academics and policy makers to collaborate on various topics of
openness and freedom. It is organized by &lt;a href="http://www.openforumeurope.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OpenForum
Europe&lt;/a>, enabling it to bridge
between the abstract academic world and policy discussions at
the European Commissions. We set out to explore focus topics to answer
current challenges to openness that the academy will develop insights
and recommendations for. These topics will shape the work of
OpenForum Academy for the near future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The workshop was opened by a series of input presentations. One of
those was on &amp;ldquo;Addressing lock-in challenges through the use of open
source software projects&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href="https://www.his.se/en/about-us/Facts-and-figures/staff/bjorn_lundell/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Björn
Lundell&lt;/a>,
a fellow of the academy and professor at the University of Skövde in
Sweden. He explained for example the need for open source solutions to
read and write data formats of digital assets of long-term
importance.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-standard-and-file-format-lock-in">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Standard and File Format Lock-In" srcset="
/media/img/post/2019-09-10_Lundell_OFA-workshop_Brussels_Slide4_hu8d291b392dc10072f966ead193d17207_756001_dcd68d2df68f540c1b1f3a30e5b163b6.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2019-09-10_Lundell_OFA-workshop_Brussels_Slide4_hu8d291b392dc10072f966ead193d17207_756001_b9efb7bc56e5d3159ad9136f1fedd29e.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2019-09-10_Lundell_OFA-workshop_Brussels_Slide4_hu8d291b392dc10072f966ead193d17207_756001_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2019-09-10_Lundell_OFA-workshop_Brussels_Slide4_hu8d291b392dc10072f966ead193d17207_756001_dcd68d2df68f540c1b1f3a30e5b163b6.webp"
width="60%"
height="428"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Standard and File Format Lock-In
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I presented key findings and recommendations from the
study on &lt;a href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/ec-jrc-oss-frand/">&amp;ldquo;The Role of Open Source Software in Standard Setting&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>. All this served to frame the following
discussion of potential core topics for the OpenForum Academy to focus.
OpenForum Europe champions openness in Europe, a topic that has
sprawled into numerous debates. Which ones of those are important and
warrant the development of academic papers and policy briefs?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="OpenForum Academy workshop attendees" srcset="
/media/img/post/2019-09-OFA-workshop_hu8e638188a6937bd07708cddf65e33c5a_503509_6222910029fc230ca872a420ba777c1c.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2019-09-OFA-workshop_hu8e638188a6937bd07708cddf65e33c5a_503509_4b0df9a52e790f2a176498125fb85038.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2019-09-OFA-workshop_hu8e638188a6937bd07708cddf65e33c5a_503509_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2019-09-OFA-workshop_hu8e638188a6937bd07708cddf65e33c5a_503509_6222910029fc230ca872a420ba777c1c.webp"
width="60%"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="exploring-modern-dimensions-of-openness">Exploring modern dimensions of openness&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Personally, I am primarily interested in Open Source aspects. However,
there are other dimensions of openness that cover different processes
and results. There is still a discussion of what an &lt;em>open standard&lt;/em>
is. &lt;em>Open hardware&lt;/em> works quite differently to software, because the
open specifications eventually have to be turned into physical
goods. Access to data is an angle independent from software,
specifications and hardware, and most software is made useful by the data
sets it processes. We want more scientific articles to be
available under &lt;em>open access&lt;/em> licenses, especially when they are
creating with public funding. The list of topics related to openness
is probably never-ending. Eventually, the following aspects emerged
as the currently most interesting ones:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="openness-and-the-cloud">Openness and the Cloud&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>How the transition of ICT to cloud and edge services changes the
importance of FOSS and data unsurprisingly sparked a heated debate
during the workshop. Is software freedom threatened by the rise of
cloud computing because software modifications are not required to be
shared? How can vendor lock-in and a lack of choice be overcome? Very
importantly, what is new about cloud that is different to before
(hint: it may be less than we think)? How can consumer interests be
protected and a healthy business ecosystem promoted? How can
regulation help and where does regulation overreach (think
surveillance or user profiling)? Many of these questions are about
finding the right balance, or identifying the justified intrusions
into the user&amp;rsquo;s rights to confidentiality and privacy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="open-source-as-civil-ict-infrastructure">Open Source as Civil ICT Infrastructure&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The EU invests in railroads, highways and data networks. Why does it
not invest much into
FOSS? &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/eusurvey/runner/EUFOSSA2-Survey" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FOSSA&lt;/a>
(hint: please participate in the survey!) is a good start. Much more
could be done. Civil society is stepping in to take over public
functions, as in the preservation of knowledge fostered by Wikipedia
or Software Heritage, often with little public support. What would be
a framework under which the EU and member states can invest into FOSS
development, to serve it&amp;rsquo;s own needs or to support support
sustainability goals? Can a public investment plan be developed for
the development of OSS ICT infrastructure, including goals and spends?&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="commercial-business-models-and-open-source">Commercial Business Models and Open Source&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Much has been discussed recently about the sustainability of FOSS
development, often confusing it the viability of the own business
model. Norms that form the pillars of the FOSS movement like
the
&lt;a href="https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/basics/4freedoms.en.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">four freedoms of software&lt;/a> or
the &lt;a href="https://opensource.org/osd" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Source Definition&lt;/a> embody
community culture at the expense of legalistic terminology. Recently,
models have emerged that remove some of the freedoms guaranteed by
those norms, for example in the deceptively
named &lt;a href="https://commonsclause.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Commons Clause License&lt;/a>. The
relation between FOSS and other rights like trademarks or patents is
still a much researched topic. Directly related to that are approaches
on how to valuate FOSS and FOSS based businesses to give guidance to
industry, VCs and policy makers for investment decisions. Some of our
fellows feel it is important to take a stand as a community, insist on
making it clear what FOSS really is and prevent a watering down of
standards like the Open Source Definition. There is a need to explain
the work of the wider FOSS community more clearly to illustrate how it
interacts with and contributes to society.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-to-contribute-and-get-involved">How to contribute and get involved&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The academy believes that these topic are of wide-ranging importance
to the development of the digital society and the single market in the
EU. They warrant a thorough investigation, deep analysis and a search
for solutions that connects research, industry and policy makers. We
hope to support this process by selecting these three subjects as
focus topics for the OpenForum Academy for the upcoming year. The
academy will facilitate the work of it&amp;rsquo;s fellows through workshops,
publications and other means. If you are a researcher, practitioner,
engaged in European politics or simply otherwise interested, follow
&lt;em>@OpenForumEurope&lt;/em> or
&lt;a href="http://www.openforumeurope.org/about-ofe/openforum-academy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">contact&lt;/a>
OpenForum Academy to get involved.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Gamalielsson, J. &amp;amp; Lundell, B. (2013) Experiences from implementing PDF in open source: challenges and opportunities for standardisation processes, In Jakobs, K. (Ed.) Proceedings of the 8th IEEE Conference on Standardization and Innovation in Information Technology (SIIT 2013), ISBN 3-86130-802-9, IEEE, Piscataway, pp. 39-49. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/SIIT.2013.6774572" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1109/SIIT.2013.6774572&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>An analytical review of text and data mining practices and approaches in Europe</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/ofe-tdm/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/ofe-tdm/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="policy-recommendations-in-view-of-the-upcoming-copyright-legislative-proposal">Policy recommendations in view of the upcoming copyright legislative proposal&lt;/h2>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/media/img/publication/tdm/ofe-logo_hu9ec7a4a6947824361103d1580c75dc6b_7165_ebac9d3e3e0f7edc7efbd76cf34bee7f.webp 400w,
/media/img/publication/tdm/ofe-logo_hu9ec7a4a6947824361103d1580c75dc6b_7165_cbd450258820ef1d06d91cd6dec0d26b.webp 760w,
/media/img/publication/tdm/ofe-logo_hu9ec7a4a6947824361103d1580c75dc6b_7165_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/publication/tdm/ofe-logo_hu9ec7a4a6947824361103d1580c75dc6b_7165_ebac9d3e3e0f7edc7efbd76cf34bee7f.webp"
width="60%"
height="93"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This paper is based on extensive desk research, including most of the
benchmark reports, such as the European Commission funded Expert Group
Report (2014), the study by De Wolf and Partners (2014), the UK IPO’s
&amp;ldquo;Exceptions to Copyright&amp;rdquo; brief (October 2014), as well as numerous
other reports, position papers, articles and blog posts. The initial
findings have been discussed at the Round Table that OFE organised in
October 2015, the conclusions of which are available in the follow-up
White Paper. The desk research and Round Table discussion have been
complemented by a series of interviews with academics, researchers,
start-ups, and more established companies (including publishers and
infrastructure providers).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/media/img/publication/tdm/TDM-Paper-Diana-Cocoru-and-Mirko-Boehm_hu9ea9c6a72978a7a2011b0c4404992c59_162477_a04c8b130e2712538d7a7dd14b5d2059.webp 400w,
/media/img/publication/tdm/TDM-Paper-Diana-Cocoru-and-Mirko-Boehm_hu9ea9c6a72978a7a2011b0c4404992c59_162477_9dc1635b6d1214d66f73672a73730018.webp 760w,
/media/img/publication/tdm/TDM-Paper-Diana-Cocoru-and-Mirko-Boehm_hu9ea9c6a72978a7a2011b0c4404992c59_162477_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/publication/tdm/TDM-Paper-Diana-Cocoru-and-Mirko-Boehm_hu9ea9c6a72978a7a2011b0c4404992c59_162477_a04c8b130e2712538d7a7dd14b5d2059.webp"
width="60%"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure></description></item></channel></rss>