<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>KDE | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/kde/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/kde/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>KDE</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>KDE</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/kde/</link></image><item><title>The emergence of governance norms in volunteer-driven open source communities</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/fossgovernance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/fossgovernance/</guid><description>&lt;p>As a reminiscence to the early times of free software collaboration,
this paper published in October 2019 captures many moments and
thoughts from involvement in the KDE community and FSFE. It is
published as the inaugural article in the &lt;em>Journal of Open Law,
Technology &amp;amp; Society&lt;/em> that continues the 10 year history of the
&lt;em>International Free and Open Source Law Review&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/media/img/publication/jolts-cover_hu0b03649ea3daf0d3c8b0a38b3fc1851e_142084_019a059b62c5f0432205c38cdf9d1251.webp 400w,
/media/img/publication/jolts-cover_hu0b03649ea3daf0d3c8b0a38b3fc1851e_142084_9f67176dc8e6c398c4be44b13819899f.webp 760w,
/media/img/publication/jolts-cover_hu0b03649ea3daf0d3c8b0a38b3fc1851e_142084_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/publication/jolts-cover_hu0b03649ea3daf0d3c8b0a38b3fc1851e_142084_019a059b62c5f0432205c38cdf9d1251.webp"
width="60%"
height="213"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure></description></item><item><title>KDE e.V. - the Backbone of the KDE Community</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/20-years-of-kd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/20-years-of-kd/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="thoughts-and-stories-about-one-of-the-biggest-floss-communities-in-the-world">Thoughts and stories about one of the biggest FLOSS communities in the world&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This book presents 37 stories about the technical, social and cultural
aspects that shaped the way the KDE community operates today. It has
been written as part of the 20th anniversary of KDE. From community
founders and veterans to newcomers, with insights from different
perspectives and points of view, the book provides you with a
thrilling trip through the history of such an amazing geek family.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>HelW olorld! - Concurrent programming using the ThreadWeaver framework</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2014-08-11-helw-olorld/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2014-08-11-helw-olorld/</guid><description>&lt;p>Concurrent programming means creating applications that perform
multiple operations at the same time. A common problem is that the
user sees the application pause. A typical requirement is that an
operation which may take an arbitrary amount of time because it is,
for example, performing disk I/O, is scheduled for execution but
immediately taken of the main thread of the application (the one that
starts &lt;code>main()&lt;/code>). To illustrate how this problem would be solved and to
jump right into using ThreadWeaver, let&amp;rsquo;s simulate this problem by
printing &lt;em>Hello World!&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> as the asynchronous payload:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-c++" data-lang="c++">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#include&lt;/span> &lt;span class="cpf">&amp;lt;QtCore&amp;gt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="cp">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#include&lt;/span> &lt;span class="cpf">&amp;lt;ThreadWeaver/ThreadWeaver&amp;gt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="cp">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nf">main&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">argc&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">char&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">**&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">argv&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">QCoreApplication&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">app&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">argc&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">argv&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">using&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">namespace&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">ThreadWeaver&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">stream&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">()&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">make_job&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">[]()&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">qDebug&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">()&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Hello World!&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>This short but complete program written in C++11 outputs the common
greeting to the command line.&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> It does so, however, from a worker
thread managed by the global ThreadWeaver queue. The header file
&lt;code>ThreadWeaver/ThreadWeaver&lt;/code> included in line 2 contains the essential
declarations needed to use the most common ThreadWeaver
operations. The components used in this examples are the global queue,
a job and a queueing mechanism. The global queue is a singleton
instance of the ThreadWeaver thread pool that is instantiated when it
it first accessed after the application starts. A job represents
&amp;ldquo;something&amp;rdquo; that should be executed asynchroneously. In this case, the
thing to execute is a C++ lambda function that prints the welcome
message. The queueing mechanism used here is a queue stream, an API
inspired by the &lt;em>iostream&lt;/em> family of classes. ThreadWeaver builds on
top of Qt, and similar to most Qt applications requires a
QCoreApplication (or one of its descendants) to exist throughout the
lifetime of the application. Up to line 7, the program looks like any
other Qt application.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To have the job lambda function called by one of the worker threads, a
job is created that wraps it using the &lt;code>make_job()&lt;/code>. It is then handed
to the queue stream. The queue stream will submit the jobs for
execution when the queuing command is completed, that is at the
closing semicolon. Once the job is queued, one of the worker threads
will automatically pick it up from the queue and execute
it. &lt;code>ThreadWeaver::Job&lt;/code> is the unit of execution handled by
ThreadWeaver queues. Jobs are simple runnable types that perform one
task, defined in their &lt;code>run()&lt;/code> method. Some jobs wrap a
lambda function as in this example or decorate other jobs. However
implementing custom, reusable job classes is only a matter of writing
a class that inherits &lt;code>ThreadWeaver::Job&lt;/code> and re-implementing
it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code>run&lt;/code> method. The job that was created by &lt;code>make_job()&lt;/code>
in this example wraps the specified lambda function, and executes it
when it is itself executed by a worker thread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The program does not specify where the job should be executed, and not
even when exactly. In a scenario where there would be many jobs
waiting in the queue, execution of the new job would not be
immediate. Which worker thread will be assigned the job is also
undefined. The programmer gives up a bit of control over the details
of execution, and in turns benefits from the automatic distribution of
jobs amongst the available processors by the worker threads in the
queue. Every program that links the ThreadWeaver library has access to
a global queue for the execution of jobs. If no queue is specified
when enqueueing a job, the global one will be used by default. Workers
threads are allocated when needed by the queue. If the global pool is
never accessed by an application, it will never be instantiated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An application performing tasks in background threads should never
exit while any of these operations is still in progress. In the case
of ThreadWeaver, this means all jobs in the queue need to be either
completed or dequeued and all worker threads idle before the
application may exit. The global pool is in fact a QObject child of
the &lt;code>QCoreApplication&lt;/code> object instantiated in line 7. It will be
deleted by the destructor of QCoreApplication. When it is destroyed,
it will wait until all queued up jobs have completed. The program will
thus wait in line 8 until the job has finished printing &amp;ldquo;Hello World!&amp;rdquo;
and will then exit. The job was enqueued as a shared pointer, so
memory management is taken care of. While this example was very much
simplified, the described functionality already has many practical
applications. For example, the many operations real-life applications
need to perform at startup, like loading translations, icon resources
et cetera, can be removed from the criticial path this way. In this
case the operations usually need to be performed in a certain order
and then handed over to the main thread. Solutions for that are built
into ThreadWeaver as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Since there have been questions - the title of the post refers to the problem of writing output from multiple threads without synchronization, which breaks the guarantees on order of execution. A boon for every concurrent program.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>The examples are part of the ThreadWeaver source code and can be found in the &lt;a href="https://api.kde.org/frameworks/threadweaver/html/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE API DOCS&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>KDE Frameworks 5 Tech Preview released, with updated ThreadWeaver</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2014-01-07-kde-frameworks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2014-01-07-kde-frameworks/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today, the KDE Community &lt;a href="http://dot.kde.org/2014/01/07/frameworks-5-tech-preview" target="_blank" rel="noopener">released a tech preview of the upcoming KDE
5
Frameworks&lt;/a>,
the new, modularised incarnation of what was previously distributed
simply as the KDE libraries. The new frameworks are drop-in extensions
to Qt applications, with minimal and well-documented dependencies for
easier deployment. The tech preview contains two frameworks that are
marked as mature, namely KArchive and ThreadWeaver. The updated
ThreadWeaver was my major piece of library coding work in 2013, and
was finished just in time for the release. Even though it is a tech
preview, it is stable, and no major (or even significant but minor)
changes in the current API are expected until the final
release. Programmers are already encouraged to use it, and provide
feedback and bug reports.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Recycled Paper Weaving" srcset="
/media/img/post/2014-01-07-weaving_huc8ec5acf46b1ae12e7aa9cfc79db2e80_262694_55ef0e7e90032ace5ae5d1f43bbf7101.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2014-01-07-weaving_huc8ec5acf46b1ae12e7aa9cfc79db2e80_262694_5ed878cde768578fe581f66754e24041.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2014-01-07-weaving_huc8ec5acf46b1ae12e7aa9cfc79db2e80_262694_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2014-01-07-weaving_huc8ec5acf46b1ae12e7aa9cfc79db2e80_262694_55ef0e7e90032ace5ae5d1f43bbf7101.webp"
width="60%"
height="720"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>ThreadWeaver is a concurrent execution scheduler written in
C++. Available for all target platforms of the Qt framework, including
desktop, mobile and embedded environments, ThreadWeaver delivers
concurrent execution of tasks, load balancing with regard to
user-defined criteria, multiple independent queues, processing graph
modelling, aggregate jobs and other comprehensive features. As all
other KDE frameworks, ThreadWeaver is Free Software. Its only
dependency is Qt, which makes it a tier 1 framework in KDE&amp;rsquo;s lingo.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A number of the &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/mirkoboehm/thread-weaver-in-kde-frameworks-5%22" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new features of
ThreadWeaver&lt;/a>
were announced at Akademy 2013. Jobs, the unit of concurrent execution
in ThreadWeaver, are now managed by the queue using shared pointers,
meaning that auto-delete behaviour is implicit and controlled by the
user. Helper templates are available to queue stack or member
variables, so allocation of jobs can be static or dynamic. Functors or
lambda functions can be used to construct jobs. Job aggregates like
collections and sequences now execute their own run() method before
queueing their elements, so that aggregates can generate their own
elements. Success and queueing state of jobs are now integrated into a
single status. Jobs can signal the result of execution by setting a
status, but also using exceptions, simplifying error reporting in more
complex job classes. Jobs can be decorated, and no more inherit
QObject by default. Decorators can be used to add signals, change
priorities or modify just about any behaviour of jobs independently of
the actual job class used. The construction of the global queue can
now be customised using a queue factory. The QueueStream API greatly
simplifies queueing jobs with a familiar iostream-like C++ syntax.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>ThreadWeaver follows the Unix idiom of doing one thing, and doing it
right. Similar to how small Unix programs can be combined to create an
practically infinite space of computing solutions, ThreadWeaver offers
itself to programmers as an add-on module with minimal
dependencies. Including it extends an application with concurrent
scheduling capability. But the same Unix idiom is also applied in a
second sense. Within ThreadWeaver, a few basic concepts – jobs and
their aggregates, queues and policies – are implemented that again
provide simple building blocks that can be combined creatively,
offering a vast space of potential solutions within the scope of the
application.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The history of ThreadWeaver goes back to KDE 3. The idea of
implementing a thread pool based execution scheduler that manages
dependencies between jobs was implemented as a proof of concept using
Qt 3. However it turned out to be difficult to implement and use
because of the lack of thread-safe reference counting of the
implicitly shared classes at the time. These fundamental problems have
been solved with the release of Qt 4. Additionally, the introduction
of cross-thread signal-slot connections further simplified the
communication between jobs and the application&amp;rsquo;s user interface. The
first production ready version of ThreadWeaver was released as part of
KDELibs with KDE 4.0. For KDE Frameworks 5, it was almost completely
re-written to simplify memory management of jobs, make use of new Qt 5
features like atomic variables, and in part to reflect new language
constructs in C++11 like lambda functions. ThreadWeaver comes with an
extensive set of unit tests that all pass in the tech preview (hear,
hear).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the following weeks and months, the framework will be polished and
debugged based on user feedback. Also, a series of posts here on this
blog will introduce individual ThreadWeaver concepts and features in
depth, mostly based on example programs, including contrasting it to
thread handling in Qt using QThread or Qt Concurrent. ThreadWeaver is
very close to production quality, having been tested continuously in
the last couple of months. There may still be smaller, source
compatible changes to the framework. We ask interested programmers out
there to provide feedback and bug reports to make ThreadWeaver what it
should be &amp;ndash; a worry-free, easy to use and powerful add-on to Qt that
programmers enjoy using. Have fun!&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/originalbliss/2897019812" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Image&lt;/a> by Shannan Sinclair, thanks&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>KDE rejects Fairsearch initiative claims: Free Software is competitive</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-09-kde-nope-to-fairsearch/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-09-kde-nope-to-fairsearch/</guid><description>&lt;p>The KDE community is deeply concerned by the wrong notion contained in
the recent complaint by the &lt;a href="http://www.fairsearch.org/mobile/fairsearch-announces-complaint-in-eu-on-googles-anti-competitive-mobile-strategy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fairsearch initiative
claiming&lt;/a>
that &amp;ldquo;distribution of Android at below-cost&amp;rdquo; could constitute
anti-competitive behaviour or predatory pricing. Free Software
platforms like KDE or Android are open to all actors without
discrimination and at extremely low barriers of entry. The fact that
Free Software solutions offer attractive alternatives to proprietary
closed-source offerings makes it more competitive, not less.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>KDE is one of the largest volunteer-driven Free Software&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>
communities. The KDE community builds a free platform to create user
experiences for desktop, mobile and other devices, and invites
individuals and companies to extend and build upon this platform. Our
community is a world-wide collaboration of companies and individuals
that together create programs in an openly governed development
process. Millions of users benefit from the programs that are
distributed under a Free Software license that guarantees the &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Four
Freedoms of
software&lt;/a>. This license
means that our users and contributors together create a public good
that others can redistribute or build upon.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The KDE Community calls on the European Commission to very
carefully analyze the Fairsearch complaint for attempts to reduce the
strong competition of Free Software platforms like KDE or Android to
proprietary non-free offerings. We encourage the European Commission
to understand that Free Software truly fosters innovation and
increases competition, and to protect the liberty of our contributors
and those of other communities to collaboratively create and
distribute Free Software as a common good.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-four-freedoms-force-actors-to-compete-within-markets-not-for-control-over-markets">The &amp;ldquo;Four Freedoms&amp;rdquo; force actors to compete within markets, not for control over markets&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Free Software provides a level playing field for all competitors. By
minimizing barriers of entry and eliminating discrimination of access
to formats, standards and technologies, Free Software platforms create
comparable starting positions for all actors, leaving them with
options to convince customers about (with) the functionality of their
products and the quality of their services. Lock-in and artificial
market segregation through discriminative licensing or essential
technologies are systematically reduced. In fact, the most popular
Free Software licence, the GPL, clearly forbids any kind of
discrimination of use.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consumers benefit from this openness by having choice between multiple
interoperable products and by lower prices through increased
competition. This is because Free Software implies open standards
accessible to any party willing to implement them. The Free Software
nature of the platforms fosters the proliferation of technical
understanding and skills, improving the chances for the development of
a more diverse, less concentrated technology business ecosystem. These
concrete opportunities for economic development specifically in the
European Union are endangered if Free Software platforms are penalized
because of misunderstood complaints of predatory pricing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The claim of anti-competitiveness of Free Software platforms is
untenable. Even in the extraordinary situation where only one entity
contributes to development, the licenses under which the products are
distributed explicitly rule out almost all typical forms of
anti-competitive behaviour like exclusive dealing (for example through
selective partnership licensing programs), any kind of fixed or
barrier pricing or territorial divisions often employed by proprietary
vendors. While trademarks can be used to limit platform fragmentation,
they will not leverage control over competing products based on the
Free Software platform itself. For example, Kindle Fire and Facebook
Phone are products build upon the Android Open Source Project platform
without any further restrictions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Because the open, competitive nature of Free Software platform fosters
confidence in users and vendors that the risk of undue lock-in is
minimal, an obvious trend towards de facto standardization on open
platforms is observable in many technological fields including the
mobile space. Since actors are usually not inclined to voluntarily
return to the strong lock-in of proprietary platforms, vendors of
proprietary platforms have shown a tendency towards hampering the
emergence of Free Software platforms by spreading &amp;ldquo;FUD&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fear,_uncertainty_and_doubt" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fear, uncertainty
and
doubt&lt;/a>). Volunteer-driven
Free Software communities rely on regulators to identify these
attempts and to provide protection of open innovation against the
vested interest of strong proprietary players.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion---free-software-platforms-are-competitive-by-nature">Conclusion - Free Software platforms are competitive by nature&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The KDE Community is asking the European Commission to protect the
liberty to develop and distribute platforms under accepted Free
Software licenses providing the Four Freedoms to all potential users
and to derivative works, and to recognize the overwhelming benefit to
the public provided by open and collaborative innovation processes. We
have shown that the elements of Free Software licenses largely
eliminate the possibility of anti-competitive behaviour, especially by
forbidding discrimination between users of the product. The predatory
pricing claims against Free Software platforms in the recent
Fairsearch complaint are wrong in substance and hurtful to
collaborative development and open innovation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sincerely,&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mirko Boehm&lt;br>
KDE Community&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Often referred to as “open source”. “Free Software” is the original and more accurate name which reflects all the aspects of the same phenomenon.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>KDE e.V. General Assembly 2013</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-07-18-kde-ga/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-07-18-kde-ga/</guid><description>&lt;p>tl;dr: If you are a committed KDE contributor and not a KDE
e.V. member, you are doing it wrong. If you are a KDE user, consider
helping the KDE User Working Group. Read KDE e.V.&amp;rsquo;s quarterly reports.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-the-test-vote-before-the-assembly-officially-started">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Voting at the KDE e.V. general assembly" srcset="
/media/img/post/2013-07-kde-ga_huaf89183451818f046cfc9b11bff581d8_1476085_59c65bc2fa97e3e30486b67fc3148ef0.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2013-07-kde-ga_huaf89183451818f046cfc9b11bff581d8_1476085_451dd665076a0028479e0da93df2de63.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2013-07-kde-ga_huaf89183451818f046cfc9b11bff581d8_1476085_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2013-07-kde-ga_huaf89183451818f046cfc9b11bff581d8_1476085_59c65bc2fa97e3e30486b67fc3148ef0.webp"
width="80%"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
The test vote before the assembly officially started
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://akademy2013.kde.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Akademy 2013&lt;/a> is still on its way, and as
usual the KDE e.V. General Assembly was held as a part of it. KDE
e.V. is the representation and governance body of the KDE
community. Membership in this not-for-profit association registered in
Berlin, Germany is open to all KDE contributors . Members usually
assemble once a year to coordinate, to vote on issues important to the
community and to elect representatives and board members as
needed. The highlights this year where the discussion of the role of
the Community Working Group, the report on the first activities of the
newly established Financial Working Group, and the election of one
new board member. I was the chairperson of the assembly, and this is
my inofficial report.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The role of KDE e.V. is somewhat described by &amp;ldquo;standing on the
shoulders of giants&amp;rdquo;. It is made up by community members interested
in governance matters, and represents the wider KDE community that
encompasses all non-technical and technical contributors. On one hand
KDE e.V. takes a passive stance, in that it does not directly
influence the direction the development of KDE is taking. On the other
hand it plays an important role and invariably influences the
community by receicing donations, managing funding of development
sprints and meetings, covering operational costs like hardware and
infrastructure, and of course by running the Akademy conference year
after year. This setup is reflected in the working groups that act as
focal points for various fields of interest within the
community. Working groups as established for marketing, system
administration, community, user relations and finance. Notably absent
is a development working group, it is commonly accepted that this is
not KDE e.V.&amp;rsquo;s concern. The membership elects a five person board that
coordinates the work of the KDE e.V. members and the working
groups. KDE e.V. currently has 169 active members, which is an
impressive number considering it&amp;rsquo;s non-technical focus in a
development community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The abbreviation &amp;ldquo;e.V.&amp;rdquo; stands for &amp;ldquo;eingetragener Verein&amp;rdquo;, German for
&amp;ldquo;registered association&amp;rdquo;. It functions much like a shareholders
company in which every member holds exactly one share. This means the
membership as a whole is the proprietor of all assets owned by the KDE
community, including the KDE trademark and the operational
infrastructure. A new member joins the group of joint owners of KDE -
quite a responsibility. Dictated by the principle of congruence of
power and responsibility the membership in turn assumes the right to
allocate funds, elect representatives to related communities et
cetera. Because of that, it is necessary that the KDE e.V. membership
represents the community of KDE contributors as broadly as
possible. Every committed KDE contributor is encouraged to seek
membership. Send an email to the &lt;a href="https://mail.kde.org/mailman/listinfo/kde-community" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE community mailing
list&lt;/a> to express
your interest to become a member (&lt;a href="http://ev.kde.org/getinvolved/members.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How to become a KDE
e.V. member&lt;/a>). Only
individuals can be members, organizations are invited to become
supporting members. As a bonus, supporting members are invited to
attend the general assembly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This year&amp;rsquo;s assembly started routinely with the report of the board
and the different &lt;a href="http://ev.kde.org/workinggroups/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">working
groups&lt;/a>. Official meeting minutes
will be published later, but it is fair to say that KDE&amp;rsquo;s house is
generally in good order. The board is focused on the transition of
the KDE community to an umbrella for various Free Software efforts as
described in the &lt;a href="http://manifesto.kde.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE Manifesto&lt;/a>. As
projects join the KDE Community, the existing structure of internal
representation needs to be updated to reflect the interests of these
sub-communities. As everything in KDE this is a work in progress, the
first step look rather promising. The marketing working group is
preparing a campaign to advertise the use of the upcoming KDE
frameworks on top of Qt. The treasurer and the auditors of
the accounting reported a small surplus in the fiscal year of 2012
that will be used to fund additional KDE activities
in 2013. Spending is well aligned with KDE e.V.&amp;rsquo;s goal and tightly
supervised. A new system of accounts and cost codes will provide
better insight in the income and expenses incurred by the various
activities and events.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The mission of the User Working Group established in 2012 is the give
KDE users a representation within the community and &lt;a href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-is-open-source-democratic/">involve them more
in KDE
development&lt;/a>. This
effort still needs more pickup. Growing the role of the User Working
Group is very important, since the strength of Free Software is only
realised by users and developers forming the communities together. It
will need a charter, user representatives to KDE e.V., and routine
activities of involving KDE users in development and quality
improvement efforts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Community Working Group moderates how contributors work
together. The principle of KDE e.V. assuming a passive, supporting
role is routinely challenged whenever the community asks the Community
Working Group to resolve conflicts. The KDE Manifesto makes it very
clear that KDE is an inclusive community with a strong sense for
intrinsically motivated, voluntary contribution. Exercising authority
in such a setup is tricky - it should be reduced to a minimum, however
that minimum needs to be determined in some way. Even occasional
abuse, rudeness or bad manners set the tone of the community and can
cause substantial damage. So far KDE in general lacks instruments to
control that damage effectively. Sadly, few individual cases were not
resolved for extended periods of time, causing contributors to leave
the community. The discussion of how to empower the Community Working
Group and find a generic way to manage such situations took ginormous
time, but was definitely worth it. However, it is not over. A conflict
resolution BoF session was held on Monday, and a policy will be
proposed to the membership in the weeks after Akademy. The Community
Working Group has earned a lot of respect by me and many others with
the prudent and calm way it handles these issues, especialy
considering the amount of frustration dealing with such issues can
cause. It needs the support of all of us to define how the standards
set by the KDE Manifesto and the &lt;a href="http://www.kde.org/code-of-conduct/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Code of
Conduct&lt;/a> can be achieved.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Albert Astals Cid was elected for the vacant board seat in an
incredibly tight race (a tie in the first round of voting, and a
one vote win in the second). Competitive votes like that show that
there is choice, and that the future of KDE is defined by the
contributors. Congratulations, Albert! Many thanks to both Albert and
Marta Rybczynska for their candidacy, and to everybody who grilled the
candidates during the questions and answers session. Sebastian Kügler
stepped down after being a board member since 2006 - many thanks to
him as well for all the great work he has done. Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://mail.kde.org/mailman/listinfo/kde-community" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE
Community mailing
list&lt;/a> to get
involved in KDE governance matters. Consider joining one of the
working groups to support them in their important work. At last, the
&lt;a href="http://ev.kde.org/reports/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quarterly reports&lt;/a> help in staying up to
date with KDE e.V.s work.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>KDE Akademy and Qt Contributor Summit in Bilbao, Spain</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-07-10-akademy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2013-07-10-akademy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://akademy2013.kde.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Akademy&lt;/a>, the annual conference of the
KDE community, will take place from July 13 to July 19 2013 in Bilbao,
Spain. It will be prefixed on July 12 by the general assembly
of &lt;a href="http://ev.kde.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE e.V.&lt;/a>, the charitable foundation that
supports the development of KDE. As usual, it will be followed by a
full week of frantic, collaborative hacking, birds of a
feather sessions and
mini-conferences. &lt;a href="http://qt-project.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Qt Project&lt;/a> and the KDE
Community are very close companions, and this year for the first time
the
&lt;a href="http://qt-project.org/groups/qt-contributors-summit-2013/wiki" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Qt Contributor Summit&lt;/a> will
be co-located with Akademy and take place July 14 and 15. In short, if
you haven&amp;rsquo;t been to a Free Software community conference like that,
this the one of the most awesome of them all, and the Qt Contributor
Summit only adds more greatness to it. I am on the way to it, to chair
the general assembly and to give a presentation on the concepts and
philosophy of Threadweaver.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="I am going to Akademy 2013!" srcset="
/media/img/post/2013-07-ak2013badge_hu577b0f51addf8b77b9a6a7144dde6903_10292_e49bbfba709ef2ea54225ac67a9f8df1.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2013-07-ak2013badge_hu577b0f51addf8b77b9a6a7144dde6903_10292_06e9b1b0e5fd2ae65c945f3f80e25f16.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2013-07-ak2013badge_hu577b0f51addf8b77b9a6a7144dde6903_10292_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2013-07-ak2013badge_hu577b0f51addf8b77b9a6a7144dde6903_10292_e49bbfba709ef2ea54225ac67a9f8df1.webp"
width="70%"
height="178"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Last year at Akademy,
my
&lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/mirkoboehm/meritocracy-in-kde" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Meritocracy in KDE&lt;/a> presentation
was all about meritocracy, Open Governance and how the KDE Community
can evolve to be attractive to contributors of all kinds and flavors,
especially beyond coders. KDE is headed to morph into an umbrella
community for similarily minded end-user focused Free Software
projects, based on a set of shared values and ideals. Being an ex
long-time KDE e.V. board member inevitably provides a certain high
level perspective on governance related matters, and the presentation
focused on providing food for thought for this process. It was the
conference where we drafted
the &lt;a href="http://manifesto.kde.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KDE Manifesto&lt;/a>. After long
consideration, it was published later in 2012 and represents an
excellent summary of what the community and it&amp;rsquo;s contributors believe
in. Kudos again to all who contributed to that,
especially
&lt;a href="http://ervin.ipsquad.net/tags/kde-manifesto-genesis/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kevin Ottens&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Too much of community building, politico-economic analysis and
meta-thinking is not good for mental health (besides, I do a lot of
that all year around at
the
&lt;a href="http://www.inno.tu-berlin.de" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Technical University of Berlin&lt;/a>). So
for this year, the goal was to go back to the basics, and take part in
the ongoing work to modernize KDE&amp;rsquo;s frameworks by refactoring and
updating
&lt;a href="https://api.kde.org/frameworks/threadweaver/html/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Threadweaver&lt;/a>. Real,
actual lower-level coding work, also known as pure bliss. Threadweaver
is KDE&amp;rsquo;s concurrency scheduler. It&amp;rsquo;s goal is provide an abstraction of
multithreading and concurrency suitable for developers of end-user
applications, and make it as simple as possible in the
process. Threadweaver has been in KDE since 4.0, but C++ idioms and
Qt, which it builds upon, have evolved dramatically since KDE 4 was
first released. So an update was in order. The development work on the
new version of the Threadweaver core is mostly complete, and ready to
be introduced at Akademy (all changes are in the kdelibs repository,
for the
curious). The
&lt;a href="https://conf.kde.org/en/Akademy2013/public/events/51" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presentation&lt;/a>
is suitable for newcomers as well, and will contain a programming
introduction, a chapter on Threadweaver&amp;rsquo;s philosophy and concept, and
a discussion of performance considerations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am writing this post on the direct flight from Berlin to Bilbao that
I reached after a bit of an eventfull journey to
the airport. Expecting that an nice extra 15 minutes buffer time to
account for the unexpected should be plenty, the taxi driver got
pulled over by the police for driving
at &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaceballs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ludicrous speed&lt;/a> (31 km/h
in a 20 km/h zone), then navigated around a traffic jam at
a construction site, and got delayed again when a scenic tour bus
got stuck after thinking it would be a great idea to pass through a
single lane road that was about three centimeters wider than the
bus itself (a road which, of course, we had to pass from the
other direction). I got to the airport just in time for boarding
and leisurely strolled onto the plane, since I was already
boarded. Should have accounted for 20 minutes of unexpected
events, bad planning on my part, I guess. However, the headphones are
playing Telegraph Road by the Dire Straits, and I am going to
Akademy. Looking forward to see you there, my friends. If you want to
meet me at Akademy, send me a tweet @mirkoboehm, or email to
&lt;a href="mailto:mirko@kde.org">mirko@kde.org&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Here is to a book that did not exist a week ago - 'How to understand an oil contract'</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-openoil-book/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 18:08:50 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-openoil-book/</guid><description>&lt;p>This week, &lt;a href="http://openoil.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Oil&lt;/a> project performed
a marvelous stunt -
the
&lt;a href="https://openoil.net/portfolio/oil-contracts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;Oil Contracts Booksprint&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>. &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/johnny-west-2509098" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Johnny West&lt;/a>,
&lt;a href="https://zararah.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zara Rahman&lt;/a> and their supporters gathered oil
contract experts from across the globe
at &lt;a href="http://www.schloss-neuhausen.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Schloss Neuhausen&lt;/a> to achieve
something that has never done before - create a book that explains how
to understand an oil contract. Not only did such a book not exist,
they also published it under a Creative Commons license. And because
that is not enough of a challenge, they did it all in one week.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-oil-contracts---how-to-read-and-understand-them">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Oil Contracts - How to read and understand them" srcset="
/media/img/post/2012-oilcontracts_hu2f17a8e331923dd5a5fef33ecc28956c_359540_94301c58e96dd634dd2a6ccf3373553c.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2012-oilcontracts_hu2f17a8e331923dd5a5fef33ecc28956c_359540_9aa5b60823a98da5e8a235a72519661a.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2012-oilcontracts_hu2f17a8e331923dd5a5fef33ecc28956c_359540_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2012-oilcontracts_hu2f17a8e331923dd5a5fef33ecc28956c_359540_94301c58e96dd634dd2a6ccf3373553c.webp"
width="60%"
height="556"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Oil Contracts - How to read and understand them
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Oil contracts determine the share of the oil revenue that the country
who owns the oil, the international oil companies and others
receive. From the book: &amp;ldquo;It is petroleum contracts that express how
[the] money is split and who makes what profits, just as it is the
contracts that determine who manages operations and how issues such as
the environment, local economic development, and community rights are
dealt with. The share price of ExxonMobil, the question of who carries
responsibility for Deepwater Horizon, whether Uganda will be able to
stop importing petrol, and how much it costs to heat and light homes
in millions of homes ­­ these are issues which depend directly on
clauses in the contracts signed between the governments of the world
and the oil companies. For most of the 150 years of oil production,
these contracts have remained hidden, nested in a broader secrecy that
surrounded all aspects of the industry. Governments claimed national
security prerogatives, companies said commercial sensitivity precluded
making them available.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Photo of the desk at the OpenOil booksprint" srcset="
/media/img/post/2012-img_0188_hu9ab35faa1bdd7d9de3fa0a97b3716028_209059_efe5735d97571271d9bec0282ff3016f.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2012-img_0188_hu9ab35faa1bdd7d9de3fa0a97b3716028_209059_97ee3b8eabc94540076e1201d38383fd.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2012-img_0188_hu9ab35faa1bdd7d9de3fa0a97b3716028_209059_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2012-img_0188_hu9ab35faa1bdd7d9de3fa0a97b3716028_209059_efe5735d97571271d9bec0282ff3016f.webp"
width="60%"
height="507"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>People who have attended an Open Source develoment sprint may notice
that the desk in the picture pretty much looks like at one of them. A
book sprint applies techniques and tools developed in the Open Source
world to authoring. Gather the relevant people, get them to a remote
location with little distraction, and then allow them to focus on
producing something they are passionate about. As in software, the
results are impressive. Collaborative editing tools are used to
coordinate between authors, editors and illustrators, similar to
version control. It is also noteworthy that of the different expert
that attended the sprint, all attended on a pro-bono basis or as part
of their day job.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The
&lt;a href="https://openoil.net/portfolio/oil-contracts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;How to understand an oil contract&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> book
is a good read even for people who are only casually interested in the
politics of oil. How the book was produced serves as a great example
of the Open Source way adopted by other, less technology related
sectors. And if the book contributes to making oil contracts better
understood and more comparable, the world has just become a better
place.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>It's the Free Software, stupid!</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-its-the-free-software-stupid/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2012 18:08:50 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2012-its-the-free-software-stupid/</guid><description>&lt;p>Heated discussions are going on in the KDE community in the aftermath
of the announcement of Nokia&amp;rsquo;s platform strategy change. Rationality
often goes out of the window when people feel such a change goes
against their personal values or beliefs. In the past days, I worked
on an analysis of the impact of the changes on KDAB, Qt and the Free
Software communities we work with, especially KDE. KDAB is rooted
deeply in the KDE community, and many of our developers work with Qt
and KDE for years now. We are sharing the same worries and hopes, so
the results may be interesting for others as well. This post is about
Qt, KDE, Free Software, politics, devices, markets, strategies - it
does not get much better than that. Read on.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="be-thankful-for-what-you-got">Be thankful for what you got&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We are told to judge by actions, not by words, so let us have a look
at the development of Qt since Nokia bought Trolltech, and how the KDE
community benefitted from it. It is important to stress this up front
because it is easy to forget that since then, Nokia has been a very
important benefactor. KDE is based on Qt and always relied heavily
it&amp;rsquo;s technical advances. Trolltech convinced many developers to use Qt
because of it&amp;rsquo;s superior quality and ease of use and the friendly and
inspiring developer community. But it was a small company, and could
not have afforded to forgo the license revenue made from selling
commercial Qt licenses. This revenue was the central pillar of
Trolltech&amp;rsquo;s business model. Trolltech was also in the uneasy situation
that it influenced the software industry way more than it&amp;rsquo;s small size
warranted, and attracted the attention of much larger
competitors. With the takeover, the revenue Trolltech generated was to
a large extend irrelevant to Nokia. The development framework is a
strategic asset, and selling Qt licenses is not in line with Nokia&amp;rsquo;s
core competencies. It also made perfect business sense to invest even
more resources that could never have been afforded from the license
revenue, to be able to rely on Qt as the future UI platform. This
investment resulted in huge performance improvements, new technologies
like QML, a continuous stable development process with many releases,
Qt Creator, and many other goodies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But the biggest gift Nokia ever presented us with was to relicense Qt
under the LGPL. It finally overcame the acceptance issue with Qt in
the wider Free Software space, and helped grow the Qt user base
massively. While other important safeguards like the Free Qt
Foundation were already in place, using Qt under the LGPL license is
so much less of a hurdle to take then to enforce the rights granted
through the Free Qt Foundation. Those rights can also only be executed
once, and only as an action of last resort. Without Qt under LGPL,
MeeGo would not have been accepted by the software industry. This, the
public hosting of the Qt git repo and the massive development manpower
Nokia invested in Qt benefit KDE immensely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The best part is that none of these presents can be un-given or taken
away. Qt is there to stay under the current Free Software licenses,
and the quality it gained in the recent years will also remain at
KDE&amp;rsquo;s service. There are new developments in KDE like QML and QtQuick
that KDE still has to fully make use of. Today&amp;rsquo;s Qt is a superb
platform to base the development of KDE on in the coming
years. Thanks, Nokia.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="qt">Qt&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It is an open question how these past achievements translate into the
future when it comes to Qt&amp;rsquo;s own development. From talking to business
partners and contacts at Nokia, it is pretty clear that no new
direction has been set for the Qt unit at Nokia. The announcement that
there will be no layoffs or budget cuts is comforting, but it needs to
be taken with a grain of salt. It may have all kinds of reasons, for
example personnel retention, local labor laws, maintaining an
undamaged business unit that can be sold - or the simple lack of an
updated strategy. So all these statements have to be mentally extended
with an &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;until further notice&amp;rdquo;. By definition, strategy changes do
not occur on a regular basis. Even if the Microsoft partnership is
unsuccessful (in sales figures, for example), it will take 3 to 5
years for that to be realized and the strategy to be re-evaluated. In
that time frame, there will most certainly be changes to the Qt unit
if it remains within Nokia.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="checking-the-facts-about-nokia-platforms-shipping-qt">Checking the facts about Nokia platforms shipping Qt&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Nokia plans to ship another 150 million Symbian devices with Qt
installed. The ability to do so depends heavily on the appeal of these
phones to users willing to pay more than the magical 100 Euro barrier
price. A vivid app market is necessary to reach this goal, since apps
are a major sales driver in today&amp;rsquo;s smartphones. Will companies keep
investing in the fledgling Symbian plus Qt app space? Investors shy
away from shrinking markets. Every corporate strategist tasked with
developing a product-market-matrix will put anything Symbian related
into the &amp;ldquo;de-invest&amp;rdquo; bracket. Why does the Symbian market shrink? Have
a look at the diagram that visualizes the spectrum of Nokia phones
(while creating the image I discovered how close the Qt and the
Windows Phone 7 shades of green are - a coincidence? I guess we will
never know).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-the-nokia-qt-dilemma">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="The Nokia Qt Dilemma" srcset="
/media/img/post/2012-nokia-qt-dilemma_hu0d5d37beef49274c4e61e30a7df5301e_22889_a3a12e7c6d10a6aff2715f8178d27842.webp 400w,
/media/img/post/2012-nokia-qt-dilemma_hu0d5d37beef49274c4e61e30a7df5301e_22889_146dd0e61a7e03ea14367ea30581d1a7.webp 760w,
/media/img/post/2012-nokia-qt-dilemma_hu0d5d37beef49274c4e61e30a7df5301e_22889_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/post/2012-nokia-qt-dilemma_hu0d5d37beef49274c4e61e30a7df5301e_22889_a3a12e7c6d10a6aff2715f8178d27842.webp"
width="60%"
height="156"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
The Nokia Qt Dilemma
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The lower end S30/S40 devices are becoming more attractive because
features are added to them that so far required a smart
phone. Internet access becomes more and more pervasive, and apps are
being developed for these devices now. Having a Facebook app, for
example, will be a convincing argument for those buyers who never
really wanted a clunky smartphone. Also, these not-so-dumb phones will
continue to be developed and shipped under the new strategy, resulting
in better customer acceptance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Through constantly improving hardware, the smartphones are being sold
at steadily decreasing prices. The cheapest Android phones are now at
below 100 Euro. This puts additional pressure on the sales revenue
generated by the current high-end Symbian phones. Customer acceptance
plays an important role in this segment as well. Read the latest
tweets, and half of them are in the line of &amp;ldquo;I finally got rid of my
Nokia and got an Android phone now&amp;rdquo;. Customers will shy away from a
line of phones that is already announced to be replaced. It is like
beating the proverbial dead horse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So the Symbian market segment will shrink, and with that the
importance (and clout) of Qt within Nokia. Customers do not care about
mobile OSes to a large extend. As soon as an average S40 phone will
ship apps and have internet access, the middle bracket in the above
diagram will fade away. Nokia is trying to define a &amp;ldquo;mid range phone&amp;rdquo;
segment between the feature phones (S30/S40) and the smartphone (WP7)
ranges. This segment is not established in the phone market, and it is
questionable whether there will be a niche for it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Because of that, app developers will hesitate to invest in the
platform, and the Qt mobile ecosystem will be under a lot of
pressure. In all the Nokia devices, Qt will not gain the widest
coverage of all development platforms. Very likely it will be S30/S40,
by device count, and WP7, by sales volume. Remember this is about Qt
within Nokia. It only influences KDE indirectly, by defining Qt&amp;rsquo;s role
in the platform strategy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="qt-on-other-mobile-platforms">Qt on other Mobile Platforms&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>With apps currently being developed in Java for the S30/S40 based
phones, Nokia uses 3 different development platforms for it&amp;rsquo;s phone
lineup, Java, Symbian with Qt, and WP7.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a hopelessly romantic rumor that Qt support might come for
the S30/S40 platform. A reality check is needed here. The low-end
devices are shipping with S30/S40 because it is available today, not
because it is a great modern future-proof platform. The apps for these
phones are being developed now, or within the next twelve months. Even
if a full-scale Qt port is started today, it won&amp;rsquo;t be available
short-term. No doubt the Qt community will be able to pull off that
stunt. But finishing the port is one thing, getting it through quality
acceptance and to the point where it is shipped in devices is
another. App developers would only target those devices when they
gained a sufficient market share, and by that time, an Android phone
sells for 50 Euro. Because of that, I do not think there will be an
official strategy to make Qt available on S30/S40. And since Qt is
also not coming to to WP7, Qt&amp;rsquo;s cross platform claim is moot within
Nokia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the Qt ports to Androids, Blackberries, Badas and Kindles become a
viable reality, other vendors will sell more devices supporting Qt
than Nokia. And that is a development going on now, while Nokia will
need between one and two years to release the first WP7 phone. These
forces will heavily impede Nokia&amp;rsquo;s ability to differentiate based on
the features of Qt, and result in less motivation to base a future
strategy on Qt as a disruptive technology. The disruption will happen
while Nokia is developing it&amp;rsquo;s first WP7 phone.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="open-governance-of-qt">Open Governance of Qt&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Regarding Open Governance, it is another open question if this strategy is
viable for Qt in the absence of a major investor (of time and money)
that drives the development. There is a good chance that it ends up
like XFree.org and produces little more than bike shedding for a long
time. Free Software projects under Open Governance, like the Linux
kernel, or X.org, or - not quite the same, but very similar - the C++
standard, tend to innovate slowly. Because of that, I am not convinced
that an impressive Qt 5 can be developed by the community under Open
Governance in a reasonable time frame. Do not get this wrong: The idea
is great, the problem is that it might not work out as we all hope
for. Three major scenarios come to mind when thinking about the future
of Qt&amp;rsquo;s governance:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Nokia considers Qt a strategic asset, and continues to heavily
invest in it. In this case, Open Governance has a chance to
succeed, but might not be in Nokia&amp;rsquo;s own interest, since it will be
losing control over it&amp;rsquo;s own important technology.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Qt is switched into maintenance mode, because it is not seen as
important for the future. In this case, Open Governance will have a
hard time to be implemented in the first place, and partners will
hesitate to take responsibility for individual modules.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nokia plans to sell the Qt unit as an asset. In this case, the
potential buyer will want enforceable control over it&amp;rsquo;s
investment. For that plan, Open Governance devalues Qt as a
sellable product. The biggest challenge for the transition to Open
Governance is to make sure the companies invested in Qt support it
fully, and want to see it happen.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Maybe I missed a scenario that will make it work? Please post your
feedback.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The biggest challenge for Qt itself will be the potential talent
drain. Qt attracted excellent developers from all over the world
because it was innovative and elite. Those are people that won&amp;rsquo;t be
comfortable with being parked on the back burner, and might not feel
at home with Nokia anymore. At the same time, they do not exactly have
problems finding another job. It will be hard for Nokia to convince
employees not to leave, and also to hire new talent of the same
quality. This is a long-term threat to the quality of Qt, and it&amp;rsquo;s
ability to innovate.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="countering-the-threat-of-free-software-in-the-mobile-market">Countering the &amp;ldquo;threat&amp;rdquo; of Free Software in the mobile market&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Android based devices and Nokia smartphones together make up 64% of
the global smartphone market at the time of this writing, according to
Wikipedia (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smartphone%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smartphone)&lt;/a>. If Nokia would
have successfully transitioned to a MeeGo based smartphone line with
Qt GUIs, the majority of the mobile devices market would use Free
Software based development tools, on open and inviting ecosystems for
developers, a competitive app market with low entry barriers, all in
all promising innovation and affordable devices. Nokia was looking for
a solution for it&amp;rsquo;s future platform problem, and it was determined to
base it on Free Software. The stock market loved the idea. Google
agreed, too, and made Android.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the same time, market demand for Windows based phones is at an
overall low. There is simply no need for another closed proprietary
phone OS, considering the alternatives. The tendency of it becoming an
accepted standard that phone software platforms should be based on
Free Software threatens Microsofts investment in WP7, and it&amp;rsquo;s general
position as a closed operating system vendor. WP7 was a solution
looking for a problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is probably a large overlap of institutional investors in Nokia
and Microsoft, given that they are both market leaders and publicly
traded companies. Both companies see their markets under siege, and
are not doing very well, so it might have sounded like a good idea at
the time to combine the hardware vendor looking for a phone OS with
the phone OS vendor looking for hardware. The partnership is
unbalanced though, because if it fails, Microsoft will still be the
market leader in PC OS installations, and Nokia will have lost
relevance in the global smart phone market. The stock market did not
love that idea so much.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But it is seriously hard to believe that simply pushing WP7 to the
market was Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s only motivation. Also, there are other vendors
that started offering WP7 phones. So why Nokia? There must be another
compelling reason for Microsoft to first send a top-ranking emissary
to Nokia, and then form a partnership that by all the usual criteria
looks like a takeover. This reason that was important enough for
Microsoft to invest billions into Nokia was to battle Free Software in
it&amp;rsquo;s emerging mobile market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The strategic goal of ensuring that future phone OSes are based on
proprietary and in particular not on Free Software was very likely the
major motivator for Microsoft to pursue this unequal partnership. The
recent ban of Free Software from the Microsoft app store indicates a
similar motivation. Nokia&amp;rsquo;s Free Software based platform strategy is
dead, and it will not come back. This means Microsoft achieved one
strategic goal immediately by establishing the partnership and
aborting Nokia&amp;rsquo;s Free Software based efforts. If this move was about
WP7 introduction into the market, why rely on the stumbling giant
Nokia, and not on one of the hungry Asian tigers, like HTC, who are
already offering WP7 phones? Because those did not have a Free
Software based strategy. Maemo or MeeGo together with Android are a
thought unbearable to Microsoft.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>About Qt - Qt was a compelling toolkit that developers loved to work
with before Nokia bought it. That is the real reason for it&amp;rsquo;s
success. Developers tell their managers that they want to use Qt
rather than something else. That quality of Qt has gotten even
better. This is why I think Qt will continue to be strong and - after
the shakeout happening now - to grow in both the Free Software and the
commercial development spaces. Qt reputation with decision makers has
been damaged, though. They regarded it not only as stable from a
software point of view, but also as being trustworthy from a
development process and maintenance point of view. This image has been
severely tarnished. So for now, the Qt market will shrink because
mobile users will leave, and it will recover and grow at a slower rate
afterwards due to the reduced willingness of developers and decision
makers to invest in it. The change of pace might be a good thing for
Qt itself after the recent coding marathons it went through. The
trolls will work hard on keeping Qt the best and one and only true
cross-platform UI toolkit on the planet. I wish them all the best for
the turbulent time to come. Hug a troll, everybody!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>About KDE - KDE as a technology will not be affected much right
now. Qt is Free Software and does not change over night. There are
enough great new features that KDE still has to digest. Even the
longer term outlook of the strategy for Qt only has an indirect effect
on KDE. Not many developers joined KDE because of the prospect of Qt
on mobile phones, so even the community will remain stable. The
development focus of Qt becomes broader again, away from concentrating
on features for the mobile space. Whether Nokia will continue to
support KDE at the same scale as in the last years is mostly a PR
decision, so it is also not related to the more technical aspects
described above. It will depend on the friendly relationship that has
been developed so far, and how it continues. Nonetheless, the next KDE
version will be shipped on time. KDE is in good shape.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>About Free Software - Nokia&amp;rsquo;s strategy change is a very sad
development in this regard, because it is not just about Qt. Microsoft
is trying to prevent Free Software from becoming mainstream in the
mobile space. Beside the feeling that it is already too late for that,
the process raises the question if such activity against the GNU
competition should be concerning the regulators. Antitrust and other
market law protects businesses from unfair competition, but
unfortunately it does not protect Free Software communities or
projects from being bullied. Indirectly preventing a competitor from
entering the market, for example, can be a reason for the antitrust
agencies to not approve such a partnership, but only if large
businesses are involved that are able to prevent the usual market
forces from working. This is a political issue, and needs to be
brought forward to policy makers. Our interests, those of Free
Software as a force to create better working and more competitive
markets, are not sufficiently represented there. That is why I will
join the FSFE.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks for reading.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>When the bazaar sets out to build cathedrals</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/beautifularchitecture/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/publication/beautifularchitecture/</guid><description>&lt;p>The book is a collection of articles about software design with a
focus on FOSS. It tries to answer the question: &amp;ldquo;What are the
ingredients of robust, elegant, flexible, and maintainable software
architecture? Beautiful Architecture answers this question through a
collection of intriguing essays from more than a dozen of today&amp;rsquo;s
leading software designers and architects. In each essay, contributors
present a notable software architecture, and analyze what makes it
innovative and ideal for its purpose.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All royalties from the book have been donated to Doctors Without Borders.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/media/img/publication/beautifularchitecture_hu8963485753fe74f2b192c4330507bad6_1033357_224cb7f4233d93a03bc599e70438195f.webp 400w,
/media/img/publication/beautifularchitecture_hu8963485753fe74f2b192c4330507bad6_1033357_460c7cc220ec699389a816a9e828edba.webp 760w,
/media/img/publication/beautifularchitecture_hu8963485753fe74f2b192c4330507bad6_1033357_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/publication/beautifularchitecture_hu8963485753fe74f2b192c4330507bad6_1033357_224cb7f4233d93a03bc599e70438195f.webp"
width="60%"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure></description></item></channel></rss>