<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Golang | Creative Destruction &amp; Me</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/golang/</link><atom:link href="https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/golang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Golang</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/icon_hu6d5c0a1cf86d6921b8114cd615c4b739_24855_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Golang</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/tag/golang/</link></image><item><title>shelldoc 0.91: go test ./...</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2026-02-19-shelldoc-091/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2026-02-19-shelldoc-091/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today marks the release of
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mirkoboehm/shelldoc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shelldoc&lt;/a> version 0.91, the
second release candidate on the road to 1.0. This release focuses on
code quality and test coverage. &lt;code>shelldoc version&lt;/code> now reports the
correct version even when installed via &lt;code>go install&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="whats-new-in-091">What&amp;rsquo;s new in 0.91?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This release emphasizes stability and maintainability:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Expanded test coverage&lt;/strong> across all major components including CLI
commands, tokenizer, and JUnit XML output generation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved API documentation&lt;/strong> with godoc comments added to all
exported functions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Code quality improvements&lt;/strong> fixing non-idiomatic boolean
comparisons and other style issues&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Removed experimental regex matching&lt;/strong> which was incomplete and not
ready for production use&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="why-focus-on-tests-and-code-quality">Why focus on tests and code quality?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Comprehensive test coverage boosts confidence that future changes
won&amp;rsquo;t introduce regressions. Once shelldoc reaches 1.0, development
will change to an on-demand release model: Every bug fix will trigger
a patch release. Every new feature will trigger a minor
release. Mirko&amp;rsquo;s whims will decide when a major release is made
(possibly never). Clean, idiomatic code simply makes the project more
maintainable and welcoming to contributors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The incomplete regex matching was removed because it&amp;rsquo;s unclear whether
it&amp;rsquo;s needed. If you are sad to see it go, feel free to submit a feature
request by creating a GitHub issue. Or a pull request, of course.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="installation">Installation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Install shelldoc with Go:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">go install github.com/mirkoboehm/shelldoc/cmd/shelldoc@v0.91.0
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="road-to-10">Road to 1.0&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Version 0.91 is the second of three planned release candidates. The
final release candidate is expected in early March, with the stable 1.0
release to follow shortly after.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you maintain documentation with shell command examples, I encourage
you to try shelldoc in your CI pipeline. Feedback and contributions are
welcome at the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mirkoboehm/shelldoc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub repository&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>shelldoc is free and open source software, licensed under GPL v3 for
the command-line tools and LGPL v3 for the reusable library components.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>shelldoc 0.90: Testing Shell Commands in Markdown Documentation</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2026-02-05-shelldoc-090/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/post/2026-02-05-shelldoc-090/</guid><description>&lt;p>I am happy to announce the relaunch of
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mirkoboehm/shelldoc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shelldoc&lt;/a> with version 0.90.
After a maintenance hiatus, I have taken over active maintenance of
shelldoc again in 2026. This release marks the first of three planned
release candidates on the road to a stable 1.0 version.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-shelldoc">What is shelldoc?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>shelldoc tests Unix shell commands embedded in Markdown
documentation. It parses Markdown files, identifies code blocks
containing shell commands, executes them, and verifies that the output
matches the documented expectations. This ensures that your
documentation examples remain accurate and up-to-date as your software
evolves.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consider a simple example in your README:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>$ echo Hello
Hello
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>shelldoc will execute &lt;code>echo Hello&lt;/code> and verify that the output matches
&amp;ldquo;Hello&amp;rdquo;. If documentation and reality drift apart, shelldoc will catch
it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-does-this-matter">Why does this matter?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Documentation rot is a common problem in software projects. Examples
that worked when written become outdated as APIs change, dependencies
evolve, or behavior is modified. Users following outdated instructions
encounter errors, leading to frustration and support burden.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By integrating shelldoc into your CI pipeline, every pull request
automatically validates that documented shell commands still work as
described. The tool produces JUnit XML output that integrates with
common CI systems, providing visual test reports for documentation
accuracy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="whats-new-in-090">What&amp;rsquo;s new in 0.90?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This release focuses on modernization and stability:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Bug fixes and security improvements&lt;/strong> addressing issues
accumulated during the maintenance hiatus&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Modernized to Go 1.21&lt;/strong> with updated dependencies&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>GitHub Actions CI&lt;/strong> with visual test result reports&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved documentation&lt;/strong> including security considerations and
limitations&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="installation">Installation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Installing shelldoc is straightforward with Go:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">go install github.com/mirkoboehm/shelldoc/cmd/shelldoc@v0.90
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="road-to-10">Road to 1.0&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Version 0.90 is the first of three release candidates planned before
the stable 1.0 release. I plan bi-weekly releases until stable,
incorporating feedback and addressing issues discovered during testing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Testing and experimentation are encouraged. If you maintain
documentation with shell examples, I would appreciate feedback on how
shelldoc works for your use case. Contributions and pull requests are
welcome at the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mirkoboehm/shelldoc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub repository&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>shelldoc is free and open source software, licensed under GPL v3 for
the command-line tools and LGPL v3 for the reusable library components.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>shelldoc</title><link>https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/shelldoc/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.creative-destruction.org/project/shelldoc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Markdown is widely used for documentation and README files that explain
how to use or build software. Such documentation often contains shell
commands demonstrating how to build or run it. To ensure documentation
remains accurate and up-to-date, it should be automatically
tested. shelldoc tests Unix shell commands in Markdown files and
reports the results.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>shelldoc parses Markdown files, identifies code blocks containing shell
commands, executes them, and verifies that the output matches the
documented expectations. It produces JUnit XML output for CI
integration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I relaunched shelldoc in 2026 after a maintenance hiatus. Version 0.90
is the first of three release candidates on the road to 1.0, featuring
bug fixes, security improvements, modernization to Go 1.21, and GitHub
Actions CI with visual test reports.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/media/img/project/shelldoc-screenshot_hu9840ecc1a907ff15c9ea7f4855265212_119524_176b641445b10ee63cc0dbdeaec19656.webp 400w,
/media/img/project/shelldoc-screenshot_hu9840ecc1a907ff15c9ea7f4855265212_119524_56de7d16f3de46d78e097090c16b05ef.webp 760w,
/media/img/project/shelldoc-screenshot_hu9840ecc1a907ff15c9ea7f4855265212_119524_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://www.creative-destruction.org/media/img/project/shelldoc-screenshot_hu9840ecc1a907ff15c9ea7f4855265212_119524_176b641445b10ee63cc0dbdeaec19656.webp"
width="760"
height="417"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://github.com/mirkoboehm/shelldoc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>shelldoc&lt;/code> project&lt;/a> is
hosted on GitHub. Contributions are welcome.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>